<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog</id>
    <title>OpenRefine Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog"/>
    <subtitle>OpenRefine Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/img/openrefine_logo.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for help with Windows and MacOS packaging]]></title>
        <id>/2022/09/30/windows-macos-packaging</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/09/30/windows-macos-packaging"/>
        <updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine's packaging for MacOS and Windows could be improved in many ways, and we are looking for help in this front.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenRefine's packaging for MacOS and Windows could be improved in many ways, and we are looking for help in this front.
We are looking for proposals from prospective contractors to improve the install experience of OpenRefine on MacOS and/or Windows.
After a similar effort on Ubuntu/Debian packaging, this initiative is meant to improve the user experience on other platforms, to lower the install barrier for a broader audience.
This project is funded by an <a href="https://cziscience.medium.com/advancing-diversity-and-inclusion-in-scientific-open-source-eaabe6a5488b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EOSS Diversity and Inclusion grant</a> from <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CZI</a>.</p><p>We are hoping that those proposals could solve some of the following issues:</p><ul><li>(MacOS) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/5205" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Provide an Applications shortcut in the DMG distribution, with a suitable background (#5205)</a></li><li>(MacOS) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/2191" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sign and notarize our DMG distribution (#2191)</a></li><li>(Windows) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/3224" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Offer a proper installer / uninstaller on Windows (#3224)</a></li><li>(Windows) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/3221" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Give an easier way to start and stop OpenRefine with a system tray integration and log viewer (#3221)</a></li><li>(Windows) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/3057" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Configuration for OpenRefine on Windows should use only 1 config file (.ini) (#3057)</a></li><li>(Windows) <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/3003" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sign openrefine.exe to eliminate extra security warnings (#3003)</a></li></ul><p>All new packaging steps should be integrated in our Continuous Deployment infrastructure (currently running on GitHub Actions), if not in our Maven packaging configuration itself.</p><p>We have funding to contract out this work to freelancers.
To respond to this opportunity, please send the following to <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org</a>:</p><ul><li>a short description of the changes you propose to introduce and how they relate to the issues above</li><li>your price for this work</li><li>any pointers to some related work in other projects (or anything that can help us assess your ability to carry out the proposed work)</li></ul><p>You are encouraged to discuss your proposed changes (such as the packaging tools you intend to use) with the contributor community (such as on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine-dev/?pli=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">openrefine-dev</a> mailing list or in GitHub issues).</p><p>Proposals will be reviewed by our <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/blob/master/GOVERNANCE.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">project director and advisory committee</a>. Feel free to get in touch with us if you have any questions about this call.</p><p><em>OpenRefine is fiscally sponsored by Code for Science and Society (CS&amp;S). CS&amp;S is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization thereby creating a culture that allows us to better serve our clientele, our employees and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our colleagues and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one's employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[From mailing lists and Gitter to a web-based Discourse forum: welcoming your feedback]]></title>
        <id>/2022/09/20/discourse</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/09/20/discourse"/>
        <updated>2022-09-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[tl;dr We consider moving OpenRefine's mailing lists and Gitter to a web-based Discourse forum, and invite your feedback.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/2022-group-discussions.jpg" alt="Simple graphic showing group discussions with multicolored text balloons" class="inset"><p><strong>tl;dr We consider moving OpenRefine's mailing lists and Gitter to a web-based Discourse forum, and invite your feedback.</strong></p><p><em>This message has also been posted on OpenRefine's <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">user</a> and <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine-dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine-dev/</a> mailing lists on September 20, 2022.</em></p><p>For quite a while, some active OpenRefine community members (<!-- -->[Antonin]<!-- -->(<a href="https://github.com/Antonin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/Antonin</a> Delpeuch), <!-- -->[Sandra]<!-- -->(<a href="https://github.com/Sandra" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/Sandra</a> Fauconnier), and the <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/blob/master/GOVERNANCE.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine advisory committee</a>) have been talking about ways to make OpenRefine’s community more lively, active and diverse.</p><p>As one step, we consider moving the current main community communication channels (the <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">user mailing list</a>, <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine-dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developer mailing list</a>, and the <a href="https://gitter.im/OpenRefine/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gitter chat</a>) to a public, web-based forum, using the <a href="https://www.discourse.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discourse</a> software. After the move, we will not delete the mailing lists, but  keep them read-only as a public archive. We feel inspired to move  forward to this, because in <a href="https://openrefine.org/blog/2022/06/28/2022-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our latest user survey (held in April-May 2022)</a>, a web-based forum was the most popular option when we asked you for your preferred means of communications.</p><p>Our choice would be a <a href="https://www.discourse.org/pricing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">hosted web-based Discourse forum</a>, on a URL like forum.openrefine.org or similar. We would go for  Discourse for many reasons. First, because it is well-designed and  widely used open source forum software, but (among other things) also  because it allows much more diverse discussion on 'smaller' topics (e.g. translation of OpenRefine's interface; discussion about larger feature  requests; threads in languages other than English...). Discourse offers  mailing list / email modes for people who prefer this as their main mode of communications.</p><p><strong><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1PY0T6dudVO6iQAbf1EUEdL1UTHu7eSFamJjL22ELMEI/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">We collected many considerations and pros/cons in this document, including the other options we could consider.</a></strong> We invite your comments and feedback <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1PY0T6dudVO6iQAbf1EUEdL1UTHu7eSFamJjL22ELMEI/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">there</a>, or on OpenRefine's mailing list. Also, if anyone is interested in helping with the move, please let me know :-)</p><p>Tentative timeline for the move (our team is small, so this may be slower, or faster if a few of you volunteer to help!):</p><ul><li>September 20, 2022 - OpenRefine’s community is informed about this plan; you can respond and comment for two weeks (and longer if we notice it is needed)</li><li>Week of Oct 3, 2022 (or later) - Decision go/no go based on your feedback</li><li>If there is general consensus: around the first weeks of November  (depending on availability of Antonin, Sandra and volunteers) - start of actual migration to Discourse</li><li>If there is general consensus: end November 2022 - OpenRefine’s  community uses Discourse for communications and mailing lists are now  read-only!</li></ul><p>Looking forward to your comments and feedback!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine's 2022 user survey: the results are in!]]></title>
        <id>/2022/06/28/2022-survey-results</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/06/28/2022-survey-results"/>
        <updated>2022-06-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Every two years, OpenRefine holds an extensive survey among its users. Our fifth edition was live in April-May 2022. No less than 207 people participated, which  breaks our record of 2020 when we received 178 responses.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every two years, OpenRefine holds an extensive survey among its users. Our fifth edition was live in April-May 2022. No less than 207 people participated, which  breaks our record of 2020 when we received 178 responses.</p><p>This year's survey was a bit more extensive than the previous ones (in <a href="http://googlerefine.blogspot.ca/2012/10/google-refine-usage-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2012</a>, <a href="http://openrefine.org/blog/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2014</a>, <a href="http://openrefine.org/blog/2018/07/16/2018-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2018</a> and <a href="https://openrefine.org/blog/2020/02/20/2020-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2020</a>); we now also included questions related to support and communications in the community. For the first time, we also asked you to give the software a general score. On average, survey respondents gave OpenRefine a solid 8 out of 10! This makes the team very happy, and of course (with your help) we hope to improve this score even more over time.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-overall-score.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-overall-score.png" class="inset"></a><p>Now, on to more details.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="who-are-you">Who are you?<a class="hash-link" href="#who-are-you" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In our 2020 survey, librarians (37.64%) formed an overwhelming majority of respondents. This year, we very proactively reached out to many of OpenRefine's typical user communities; this has resulted in a more 'even' distribution of sectors and communities that our survey respondents hailed from. Based on new popular answers in previous surveys, we added a few extra options to the question "Which field(s), discipline(s) or community/ies do you most identify with?" and respondents could provide more than one answer. Today, librarians are still the largest group of OpenRefine users (15.1%), followed by cultural sector professionals (11.6%), Linked Open Data / semantic web aficionadas (11.2%), researchers (10.1%) and data scientists (9.5%).</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-communities.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-communities.png" class="inset"></a><p>The vast majority of people use OpenRefine professionally, but 14.9% of our users do indicate that they mainly use the software in their free time. Unsurprisingly, many of them indicate that they are active in the Wikimedia or OpenStreetMap communities.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-work-free-time.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-work-free-time.png" class="inset"></a><p>For the first time, we asked in which language(s) you use OpenRefine (both its interface and the datasets you interact with). English is dominant with 64.1%; followed by French (9.7%), German (8.1%), Spanish (6.5%) and various other languages (3.2%).</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-languages.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-languages.png" class="inset"></a><p>2022 survey respondents use OpenRefine a bit more often than we saw in previous editions.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-how-often-use.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-how-often-use.png" class="inset"></a><p>And you are also increasingly becoming OpenRefine 'veterans', with a solid 66.7% saying that you have used the software for more than two years.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-how-long-use.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-how-long-use.png" class="inset"></a><p>You are rating your OpenRefine skill level a bit higher than in the past, too.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-skill-level.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-skill-level.png" class="inset"></a><p>You are using OpenRefine for roughly the same purposes as two years ago. We added "data imports from other resources" as a new option, and that's indeed frequently done. Analyzing existing datasets has become more popular (50.2% now), and preparing datasets before visualization in other applications is done less often (22.16%) than in 2020. Reconciliation (55.1%) also keeps (slowly) growing as a typical activity inside OpenRefine.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-tasks.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-tasks.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-does-your-openrefine-installation-look-like">What does your OpenRefine installation look like?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-does-your-openrefine-installation-look-like" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>53.4% of respondents usually update OpenRefine to its current stable release; an additional 23.8% use an earlier version of OpenRefine 3.x.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-versions.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-versions.png" class="inset"></a><p>As we expected, most people (85%) work with a local version of OpenRefine. However, nearly 10% use, or even run, a version via cloud hosting. We are aware that our users are interested in this, and are curious to see whether this number increases over time.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-local-hosted.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-local-hosted.png" class="inset"></a><p>Which plug-in(s) or extension(s) do you use in OpenRefine, if any? We have revamped this question a bit compared to previous years, because the OpenRefine extension ecosystem is in constant change. While more than 50% of users are either unaware of the existence of extensions, or don't consciously use any, the Wikidata extension (installed by default in OpenRefine) is used by no less than 26.9% of respondents. Other popular extensions are the RDF extension (8%), VIB-Bits (4%), and GeoJSON export (3.4%).</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-extensions.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-extensions.png" class="inset"></a><p>As mentioned above, reconciliation is slowly becoming more and more popular in OpenRefine. The Wikidata reconciliation service (shipped in OpenRefine by default) is quite dominant, used by 49.1% of survey respondents. VIAF (15.4%), the Getty vocabularies, and in-house reconciliation services (8.6%) follow in popularity. Under "Other", we see a few new responses from our community of users in the biodiversity domain: Bionomia and the GBIF taxonomy.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-recon.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-recon.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-do-you-perceive-openrefine">How do you perceive OpenRefine?<a class="hash-link" href="#how-do-you-perceive-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Which features make you choose OpenRefine over other tools? Many people mention that they appreciate OpenRefine's GUI, price (free!), flexibility, power, reconciliation features, and relative ease of use.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-why.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-why.png" class="inset"></a><p>Which tool(s) would you use if OpenRefine would not be available to you? Excel is a winner here, and quite a few people also mention Python and R. QuickStatements would be an important alternative for Wikimedia and Wikibase users. One user mentions they would "sob the entire time", which we of course want to prevent.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-alternatives.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-alternatives.png" class="inset"></a><p>How do you describe OpenRefine to someone else? Many of the descriptions involve the words "data", "powerful" and "cleaning", and we very much appreciate phrases like "spreadsheets on steroids", "the Ferrari of spreadsheets", "a librarian's dream", "swiss army knife", or simply "magic".</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-describe.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-wordcloud-describe.png" class="inset"></a><p>We received many feature requests as answers to the prompt "It would be awesome if OpenRefine...". Quite a few of these major requests are very familiar to us, and also mentioned on our <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Roadmap" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">roadmap</a>.</p><ul><li>Support for large datasets with many columns and/or rows (3 requests). Good news: we are working towards this goal for OpenRefine's major new 4.x release.</li><li>A better UX (3 requests), which makes it easier for newcomers to use OpenRefine (3 requests).</li><li>A free online instance of OpenRefine / hosted OpenRefine (3 requests).</li><li>Multi-user support in OpenRefine (2 requests).</li><li>Better Python support (3).</li><li>Allow working with R for syntax based work (2).</li><li>More 'point and click' functions to replace GREL (2).</li><li>Some simple data visualizations (2 requests), including the possibility to plot georeferenced data on a map.</li><li>Easier import from (2 requests) and reconciliation with external datasets via APIs</li><li>A feature to add new rows (2)</li><li>Better developed, more explicit and more detailed notifications and warnings (2)</li></ul><p>Some feature requests are specific to Wikimedia, Wikibase and Wikidata support:</p><ul><li>Faster Wikidata upload</li><li>The possibility to use OpenRefine for Wikibase editing (note: this is  already possible, see <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/next/manual/wikibase/configuration" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine's documentation</a> and <a href="https://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/OpenRefine_to_Wikibase:_Data_Upload_Pipeline" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a tutorial on Wikiversity</a>)</li><li>Clearer error messages when Wikidata edits fail</li></ul><p>Several requests relate to reconciliation services:</p><ul><li>Faster and more powerful reconciliation</li><li>Reconciliation against a SPARQL query</li><li>More reconciliation services</li><li>Less abandoned extensions and reconciliation services (cleanup of inactive and deprecated ones)</li></ul><p>Some more requests related to usability and ease of use of OpenRefine:</p><ul><li>Drag and drop for columns</li><li>Keyboard accessible GUI</li><li>Dark mode</li><li>A language that is more accessible than regex</li><li>Auto-update when new versions become available</li></ul><p>Some requests relate to the way in which OpenRefine works with, and stores, files:</p><ul><li>More transparent way to store files</li><li>Integration in OpenOffice/LibreOffice</li><li>Dynamic links with Google Sheets</li></ul><p>Requests related to exporting data:</p><ul><li>Improved workflow handling, including import/export and multi-project history</li><li>Preserve hierarchical structure of a dataset and export it too</li><li>Upload data directly into database</li><li>Better encoding of diverse characters during export</li></ul><p>And finally:</p><ul><li>More clustering algorithms</li><li>Improved record mode</li><li>Parse JSON or XML automatically</li><li>API calls beyond get</li><li>Make OpenRefine suited for georeferencing</li><li>More training (including in underrepresented contexts)</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="communication-help-and-support">Communication, help and support<a class="hash-link" href="#communication-help-and-support" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>37.1% of survey respondents were unaware that OpenRefine has a user mailing list; 25.2% is subscribed to it. You can find, and subscribe to, the mailing list here: <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine</a></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-maillist.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-maillist.png" class="inset"></a><p>We asked if respondents would like to communicate with other OpenRefine users online and, if so, which channel(s) they would prefer. An online forum, like GitHub discussions or Discourse (like <a href="https://blog.openstreetmap.org/2022/03/21/a-new-discussion-forum-for-osm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">recently initiated by the OpenStreetMap community</a>) is preferred, but our current <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">mailing list</a> is also appreciated. Slack, which is heavily used in many professional contexts, comes third. Good news: we are indeed investigating if an online forum, in addition to OpenRefine's user mailing list, would be useful and maintainable.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-channels.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2022survey/2022-survey-channels.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-you-want-to-help-openrefine">How you want to help OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-you-want-to-help-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Finally, OpenRefine's 2022 survey included a question exploring in which ways the community would be willing to help the project. Many individuals and several institutions are interested in donating money, and quite a few people have indicated that they would be willing to translate OpenRefine's interface or participate in one of its committees. We thank everyone who expressed interest in this, and will follow up via email where relevant.</p><p>If you want to help translating OpenRefine's interface to your language, you can actually get started right away! <a href="https://hosted.weblate.org/engage/openrefine/?utm_source=widget" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">We offer translation via the web-based Weblate tool</a>. Just <a href="https://hosted.weblate.org/engage/openrefine/?utm_source=widget" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">click</a> to get started!</p><p>Many thanks to everyone who has completed the survey, and we wish you happy refining!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to our May 2022 Outreachy interns!]]></title>
        <id>/2022/06/19/outreachy</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/06/19/outreachy"/>
        <updated>2022-06-19T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year, OpenRefine is very happy to participate in Outreachy again, an internship program in open source and open science initiated and run by the Software Freedom Conservancy. Outreachy provides paid, remote internships to people subject to systemic bias and impacted by underrepresentation in the technical industry where they are living. For OpenRefine, this is our second time welcoming and mentoring interns who actively improve our codebase and, while doing so, gain experience in open source development.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year, OpenRefine is very happy to participate in <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Outreachy</a> again, an internship program in open source and open science initiated and run by the <a href="https://www.sfconservancy.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Software Freedom Conservancy</a>. Outreachy provides paid, remote internships to people subject to systemic bias and impacted by underrepresentation in the technical industry where they are living. For OpenRefine, this is our second time welcoming and mentoring interns who actively improve our codebase and, while doing so, gain experience in open source development.</p><img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/outreachy-logo-not-square-no-background.png" alt="Outreachy logo" width="300" class="img_ev3q"><p>Our current participation in Outreachy is part of the project <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/openrefine-for-everyone/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine for Everyone</a>, which focuses on making OpenRefine more useful for international, multilingual audiences, by removing cultural biases from the tool. This project has been generously funded by the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative (<a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/?cycle=d-i" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diversity &amp; Inclusion funding cycle</a>).</p><p>From <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/alums/2022-05/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">end May until end August 2022</a>, we warmly welcome <a href="https://github.com/elroykanye" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Elroy Kanye</a> (from Bamenda, Cameroon) and <a href="https://github.com/WaltonG" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Walton Goga</a> (from Nairobi, Kenya) to our team. Elroy works on the implementation of <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/2443" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">server-side localization</a> in OpenRefine, and is mentored by <!-- -->[Antonin Delpeuch]<!-- -->(<a href="https://github.com/Antonin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/Antonin</a> Delpeuch). Walton <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/1212" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">develops a SPARQL importer</a>, with mentorship from <a href="https://github.com/antoine2711" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Antoine Beaubien</a>. Please join us in welcoming them, and don’t hesitate to thank them for their contributions as you see them appear in our repositories!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Jan Ainali, OpenRefine's new advisory committee member]]></title>
        <id>/2022/05/05/jan-ainali-advisory-committee</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/05/05/jan-ainali-advisory-committee"/>
        <updated>2022-05-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine’s advisory committee is growing! We are warmly welcoming Jan Ainali as a new member. OpenRefine’s advisory committee runs the administrative side of the project on a day to day basis.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenRefine’s advisory committee is growing! We are warmly welcoming Jan Ainali as a new member. OpenRefine’s advisory committee runs the administrative side of the project on a day to day basis.</p><img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/2022-jan-ainali.jpg" alt="Portrait photo of Jan Ainali" width="200" class="img_ev3q"><p>Photo: Jan Ainali, CC BY-SA 4.0</p><p>Jan brings a lot of valuable experience to OpenRefine and to the advisory committee. He is an active user of OpenRefine and a volunteer in the Wikimedia movement (representing one of OpenRefine’s larger user communities). In his day job as codebase steward at the <a href="https://publiccode.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Foundation for Public Code</a> (based in Amsterdam, NL), Jan closely works with open source software projects developed by public organizations around the world. Previously, he also was (among others) a policy advisor at the European Parliament, and Executive Director of <a href="https://wikimedia.se/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Sweden</a>.</p><p>In Jan’s own words:</p><blockquote><p>Since OpenRefine fills such an important role in the ecosystem and is a valuable tool for different communities, I am glad to join the advisory board. I hope that my experience from working with open knowledge, open data and open source, as well as some organizational development, will prove useful for the OpenRefine community.  </p></blockquote><p>Welcome, Jan!</p><p>The other members of the advisory committee are Antonin Delpeuch and Martin Magdinier. You can read more about OpenRefine’s governance and community in <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/blob/master/GOVERNANCE.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our Governance document</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine welcomes Sandra Fauconnier as project director]]></title>
        <id>/2022/03/03/project-director</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2022/03/03/project-director"/>
        <updated>2022-03-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine’s advisory committee is happy to welcome Sandra Fauconnier as OpenRefine’s project director. This is a part time position, funded by an Essential Open Source Software for Science grant awarded by the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenRefine’s advisory committee is happy to welcome <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:SFauconnier" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sandra Fauconnier</a> as OpenRefine’s project director. This is a part time position, funded by an <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/openrefine-for-everyone/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science grant awarded by the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a>.</p><p>In this new role, Sandra will work closely with OpenRefine’s advisory and steering committees, and with its communities of users and contributors. She will help to improve our governance and community diversity, build community-driven structures to formalize OpenRefine’s roadmap and keep it up to date, will help us find and secure new sources of funding, and will support the advisory committee in OpenRefine’s day-to-day operations.</p><p>Sandra started using OpenRefine in 2015, and is currently using it in her free time on a nearly daily basis, mainly for batch editing data on Wikidata and Wikimedia Commons. As an art historian and active Wikimedia volunteer, she has lots of affinity with OpenRefine’s users from the cultural sector, libraries, and the Wikimedia movement. Since July 2021 she has been working with the OpenRefine team as project manager/product owner on our <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/CS%26S/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">grant with the Wikimedia Foundation to develop integration with Wikimedia Commons</a>.</p><p>Sandra is keen to get to know very diverse members from OpenRefine’s community. <a href="https://hackmd.io/JgmAzY_9RwCilSQIxkNChA?view" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Here</a> you find an open invitation, and various ways to contact her.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Join OpenRefine's Advisory Committee]]></title>
        <id>/2021/12/12/Advisory-committee-member</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/12/12/Advisory-committee-member"/>
        <updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine is seeking a new member for its Advisory Committee (unpaid position).]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>OpenRefine is seeking a new member for its Advisory Committee (unpaid position).</strong></p><p><a href="https://openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine</a> is a powerful tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than ten years and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world. OpenRefine received a two years grant from the <a href="https://www.siliconvalleycf.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silicon Valley Community Foundation</a> via the <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a> under their <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science</a> program, specifically focusing on improving Diversity and Inclusion in open source projects. OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501<!-- -->(<!-- -->c<!-- -->)<!-- -->(3) charitable organization in the USA.</p><p>Starting in 2019, OpenRefine explored a new sustainability model by leveraging grants and corporate sponsorship. Three years into that process, OpenRefine is now fiscally sponsored by Code for Science &amp; Society Inc and secured four significant grants from three different organizations. As a result, the project matured with the creation of the <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/blob/master/GOVERNANCE.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Advisory, Steering, and Code of Conduct committees</a> and started hiring contractors to advance our roadmap. During that time, we went through tremendous growth as we doubled the number of active contributors, increased the number of languages translated, and continued to see more users relying on OpenRefine.</p><p>Today we are looking for (a) new Advisory Committee member(s) to support our new model, strengthen our governance and continue to engage at an organizational level with our partners and community.</p><p>As its primary responsibility, OpenRefine's Advisory Committee oversees the project and coordinates with Code for Science &amp; Society for its operations. So far, the advisory committee has taken care of the following executive responsibilities:</p><ul><li>Manage grant applications;</li><li>Oversee hiring and management of contractors;</li><li>Prepare and approve budgets;</li><li>Work together with OpenRefine's Steering Committee to establish strategic partnerships with other communities and organizations.</li></ul><p>In the next two years, we also want to:</p><ul><li>Improve our governance and community diversity;</li><li>Renew our Advisory and Steering Committees, focusing on bringing users and institutions into the project's governance;</li><li>Formalize OpenRefine's roadmap;</li><li>Ensure the project’s financial sustainability by searching for new sources of funding</li></ul><p>We are looking into hiring a project director to support the advisory committee in those missions (see <a href="https://openrefine.org/blog/2021/11/05/Project-director.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the corresponding job posting for
details</a>).</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-position">About the position<a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-position" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We are seeking at least one new Advisory Committee member to help us pursue the goals described above, bringing their perspective on how OpenRefine should evolve.</p><p>This position is for you if you:</p><ul><li>Care deeply about the future of OpenRefine;</li><li>Have good communication skills in English;</li><li>Are able to join a monthly call with Code for Science and Society where we coordinate the project's operations.</li><li>Are ready to invest at least 3 hours per month (between calls and document review).</li></ul><p>This is a volunteer (non paid) position.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-respond">How to respond<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-respond" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please nominate yourself or other members of the community by contacting <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org.</a>
The current advisory committee will engage a conversation with the nominees and select one or more new members.
New members will be announced on our <a href="https://openrefine.org/category/blog.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">blog</a> and <a href="https://openrefine.org/category/blog.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">mailing list</a>. </p><p><em>OpenRefine is fiscally sponsored by Code for Science and Society (CS&amp;S). CS&amp;S is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization thereby creating a culture that allows us to better serve our clientele, our employees and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our colleagues and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one's employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Structured Data on Commons functionalities: welcome to OpenRefine's new team members!]]></title>
        <id>/2021/12/01/commons-project-team</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/12/01/commons-project-team"/>
        <updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine is developing features for Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons and welcomes new members to its team!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>OpenRefine is developing features for Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons and welcomes new members to its team!</strong></p><p>Earlier in 2021, OpenRefine has received a <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/CS%26S/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">project grant from the Wikimedia Foundation</a> to add functionalities for Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons (SDC). This has been a major ask from the Wikimedia community, and will provide OpenRefine with powerful features for batch editing and uploading files with structured data on <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Commons</a>, the media repository behind Wikipedia.</p><h1>Welcome to OpenRefine's new team members!</h1><p>Development has started in September 2021, and we are very happy that our team is now complete! Join us in welcoming OpenRefine's new team members:</p><ul><li><p><strong><a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Eugene233" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eugene Egbe</a></strong> is a software engineer from Cameroon. He is an active member of the African Wikimedia developers' community and has worked on various software applications in the Wikimedia ecosystem, including the ISA Tool and Scribe. For OpenRefine's SDC project, Eugene develops the Wikimedia-specific features, including a <a href="https://commonsreconcile.toolforge.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Commons reconciliation service</a>.</p></li><li><p><strong><a href="https://about.me/gomezsalazar-jogebeth" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Joey Salazar</a></strong> is a software engineer from Costa Rica, graduated in China, working in Internet Governance spaces in Europe and America. Continually advocating for free speech online and open source technologies, Joey focuses on policies, standards, and protocol implementations, in particular regarding the DNS and related privacy and censorship considerations. In the SDC project, Joey takes care of software development in OpenRefine's own codebase.</p></li><li><p><strong><a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:SFauconnier" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sandra Fauconnier</a></strong> is an art historian who has engaged with digital projects in the cultural sector for many years. She is an active Wikimedian and a prolific user of OpenRefine, and has worked for the Wikimedia Foundation as part of the team which developed Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons. Sandra acts as product manager for the SDC project in OpenRefine.</p></li></ul><p>The team is mentored by Antonin Delpeuch.</p><p>We are developing these new features in close collaboration with the Wikimedia community. You can read <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/CS%26S/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine/Timeline" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">monthly reports of ongoing work on meta.wikimedia.org</a>. Wikimedia-specific tasks are managed on Wikimedia's bug tracking system <a href="https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/tag/openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Phabricator</a>, and OpenRefine-specific development is <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/projects/10" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tracked on GitHub</a>. If you have a Wikimedia account, you can <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Global_message_delivery/Targets/OpenRefine_and_SDC" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">subscribe</a> to receive updates about the project on a talk page of your choice.</p><h1>Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons?</h1><p>What is Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons? Quite a few OpenRefine users will be familiar with <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata</a>, the multilingual Linked Open Data knowledge base of the Wikimedia movement. Since 2019, media files (digital photographs, videos, sound files, etc) on Wikimedia Commons, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Structured_data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">can also be described with multilingual linked data from Wikidata</a>.</p><p>OpenRefine already includes support for Wikidata and, more recently, arbitrary Wikibases. The new Structured Data on Commons features in OpenRefine will build further upon this.</p><p>Here's an early preview of structured data for a list of Wikimedia Commons files as displayed in OpenRefine:</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/202111-commons-SDC-wikitext.png" alt="Commons files with SDC and Wikitext in OpenRefine" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Now hiring: Part-time Project Director]]></title>
        <id>/2021/11/05/Project-director</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/11/05/Project-director"/>
        <updated>2021-11-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine is seeking a *Part-time Project Director* (paid position).]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>OpenRefine is seeking a <em>Part-time Project Director</em> (paid position).</strong></p><p><a href="https://openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine</a> is a powerful tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than ten years and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world. OpenRefine received a two years grant from the <a href="https://www.siliconvalleycf.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silicon Valley Community Foundation</a> via the <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a> under their <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science</a> program, specifically focusing on improving Diversity and Inclusion in open source projects. OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501<!-- -->(<!-- -->c<!-- -->)<!-- -->(3) charitable organization in the USA.</p><p>The OpenRefine team is seeking a Project Director to help the project grow its operations and community.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about-the-job">About the Job<a class="hash-link" href="#about-the-job" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Reports to the advisory committee </li><li>Supervises OpenRefine paid contractors</li><li>Schedule: part-time, the position can accommodate other commitments;</li><li>Duration: 24 months with possible extension as new funding is secured. </li><li>Start Date: As soon as you can! </li><li>Fully remote: you will be working with a team spread on multiple continents;</li><li>Compensation: We have a budget between USD 40,000 and 50,000 per year depending on experience, commitment, and contract type (see below)</li><li>Contract type: Code for Science &amp; Society (our fiscal sponsor) administer contract and compensation. Depending on the director's country of residence and fiscal status, the position can be a contractor or employee.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-responsibilities">Key Responsibilities<a class="hash-link" href="#key-responsibilities" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Starting in 2019, OpenRefine explored a new sustainability model by leveraging grants and corporate sponsorship. Three years into that process, OpenRefine is now fiscally sponsored by Code for Science &amp; Society Inc and secured four significant grants from three different organizations. As a result, the project matured with the creation of the Advisory, Steering, and Code of Conduct committees and started hiring contractors to advance our roadmap.  During that time, we went through tremendous growth as we doubled the number of active contributors, increased the number of languages translated, and continued to see more users relying on OpenRefine.</p><p>Today we are hiring a Project Director to support our new model, strengthen our governance and continue to engage at an organizational level with our partners and community. The project director's primary responsibility will be to lead the community by </p><ul><li>Improving our governance and community diversity;</li><li>Formalizing the project roadmap;</li><li>Ensuring the project's financial sustainability by searching for new sources of funding; </li><li>Supporting the advisory committee in the day-to-day operations. </li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="governance-inclusion-and-diversity">Governance, Inclusion, and Diversity<a class="hash-link" href="#governance-inclusion-and-diversity" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The project director will develop OpenRefine's existing governing bodies over the next 24 months, focusing on bringing users and institutions into the project's governance and increasing diversity along geographic, racial, and ethnic axes in governance. We want to develop a stronger sense of community among contributors, encouraging long-term commitment to the project and attracting new contributors.</p><p>Responsibilities include:</p><ul><li>To update the project's governance, code of conduct, and contributing documents and create a safe and welcoming space for contributors;</li><li>To develop and document governance processes to support onboarding and leadership development.</li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="project-roadmap">Project Roadmap<a class="hash-link" href="#project-roadmap" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The Project Director will work with our institutional partners, steering committee, and community to formalize and advertise the project roadmap.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="fundraising">Fundraising<a class="hash-link" href="#fundraising" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The Project Director will seek new sources of funding to ensure the project's financial sustainability. Responsibilities include</p><ul><li>To apply for funding to support the project, including grants and donations;</li><li>To report to funders;</li><li>To explore other funding models, including crowdfunding campaigns or pay for services. </li></ul><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="operation">Operation<a class="hash-link" href="#operation" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The project director will support the advisory committee and work with Code for Science &amp; Society in the day to day operations, by</p><ul><li>Acting as a representative of the project to partners and in events and responsible for communication for the project;</li><li>Leading the hiring process for contractors/employees and be the person they report to;</li><li>Coordinating OpenRefine's participation in internship programs.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="qualifications">Qualifications<a class="hash-link" href="#qualifications" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We are looking for candidates with:</p><ul><li>Experience leading open-source and/or with volunteer-run projects;</li><li>Experience implementing strategic and operational plans;</li><li>Excellent communication skills;</li><li>Proven track record of fundraising for nonprofits;</li><li>Ability to work collaboratively and non-hierarchically;</li><li>Experience in remote collaboration and communication; comfort working remotely with colleagues in multiple time zones via Github, Mailing List discussion, Online Meeting, and other related tools;</li><li>Ability to work independently and take initiatives;</li><li>Familiarity with OpenRefine as a user;</li><li>Familiarity with one or more communities where OpenRefine is popular.</li></ul><p>Not certain your credentials are a 100% match with the position description? Please apply anyway! We are looking to find the right person for our team, and we will help develop your skills during the project.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-respond">How to respond<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-respond" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please <a href="https://airtable.com/shr50thPWDtDuVSVE?prefill_Applying+for=Project%20Director" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">apply here</a> with your resume or CV, and a short letter of interest. We will schedule an interview with short-listed candidates. Applications will be reviewed on a rolling basis, starting November 10th.</p><p><em>OpenRefine is fiscally sponsored by Code for Science and Society (CS&amp;S). CS&amp;S is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization thereby creating a culture that allows us to better serve our clientele, our employees and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our colleagues and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one's employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Now hiring: Junior Developer for Structured Data on Commons functionalities in OpenRefine]]></title>
        <id>/2021/07/07/OpenRefine-SDC-developer</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/07/07/OpenRefine-SDC-developer"/>
        <updated>2021-07-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine is seeking a *Junior Developer - Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons additions to OpenRefine's codebase* (paid contractor position).]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>OpenRefine is seeking a <em>Junior Developer - Structured Data on Wikimedia Commons additions to OpenRefine's codebase</em> (paid contractor position).</strong></p><p><em><a href="https://openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine</a> is a power tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than 10 years, and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world.</em>
<em>OpenRefine is quite actively used on <a href="https://www.wikidata.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata</a>, the structured data ‘sister’ of Wikipedia. In addition, thanks to a <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">grant from the Wikimedia Foundation</a>, OpenRefine will, between September 2021 and August 2022, be extended with structured data functionalities for <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Structured_data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Commons</a>, the media repository of the Wikimedia ecosystem. This code extension will make it possible to batch edit structured data of existing files on Wikimedia Commons, and to batch upload new Wikimedia Commons files with structured data from the start.</em>
<em>OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501(c)(3) charitable organization in the US.</em></p><p>The OpenRefine team is seeking a junior developer to help extend OpenRefine’s own code base with the abovementioned functionalities.</p><ul><li>This is a part time, 8 months contract. </li><li>The work will take 35 weeks, from November 2021 until end June 2022.</li><li>For an average of 30 hours per week.</li><li>Fully remote. We encourage developers from outside of the USA and EU to apply.</li><li>We have between 36,000 USD and 42,000 USD available to complete this assignment, depending on experience. The payment details will be negotiated with the contractor, who will invoice Code for Science &amp; Society for their work towards the corresponding goals.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="responsibilities">Responsibilities<a class="hash-link" href="#responsibilities" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The Junior Developer:</p><ul><li>Reworks OpenRefine’s Wikibase extension to work with any entity type, including the <a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:WikibaseMediaInfo#MediaInfo_Entity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MediaInfo entity type</a> used on Wikimedia Commons.</li><li>Adds support for Wikibase federation in OpenRefine’s Wikibase extension, so that Wikidata items can be used in structured data generated for Commons.</li><li>Develops export and upload functionalities of media files through OpenRefine (either from harddrive or from URL)</li><li>Works in close collaboration with their colleague (Wikimedia developer), and will regularly coordinate with the product manager and the rest of the OpenRefine development team.</li></ul><p>You can read more about this project, the planned tasks and the various roles, in the <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">public grant proposal</a> on meta.wikimedia.org.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="qualifications">Qualifications<a class="hash-link" href="#qualifications" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please do not self-censor if you do not meet all of these criteria, as you will develop your skills during the project.</p><ul><li>Experience developing in Java and Javascript.</li><li>Enthusiasm for writing good documentation and tests alongside your code.</li><li>Ability to work independently in a fully remote project.</li><li>Experience with open source development workflows on GitHub.</li><li>Familiarity with Wikibase and OpenRefine as a user.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-respond">How to respond<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-respond" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please send your resume or CV, sample of your relevant previous work, and a short letter of interest to <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org.</a> We will schedule an interview with short-listed candidates. Applications will be reviewed on a rolling basis, with an aim to fill the position by July 30.</p><p><em>OpenRefine is fiscally sponsored by Code for Science and Society (CS&amp;S). CS&amp;S is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization thereby creating a culture that allows us to better serve our clientele, our employees and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our colleagues and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one’s employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Now hiring: Junior Developer for Wikimedia Commons reconciliation and batch functionalities]]></title>
        <id>/2021/07/07/Wikimedia-Commons-reconciliation-batch-developer</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/07/07/Wikimedia-Commons-reconciliation-batch-developer"/>
        <updated>2021-07-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Update (2021-08-06): both positions have been filled.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Update (2021-08-06): both positions have been filled.</em></p><p><strong>OpenRefine is seeking a <em>Junior Developer - Wikimedia Commons reconciliation and batch upload functionalities</em> (paid contractor position).</strong></p><p><em><a href="https://openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine</a> is a power tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than 10 years, and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world.</em> </p><p><em>OpenRefine is quite actively used on <a href="https://www.wikidata.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata</a>, the structured data ‘sister’ of Wikipedia. In addition, thanks to a <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">grant from the Wikimedia Foundation</a>, OpenRefine will, between September 2021 and August 2022, be extended with structured data functionalities for <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Structured_data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Commons</a>, the media repository of the Wikimedia ecosystem. This code extension will make it possible to batch edit structured data of existing files on Wikimedia Commons, and to batch upload new Wikimedia Commons files with structured data from the start.</em></p><p><em>OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501(c)(3) charitable organization in the US.</em></p><p>The OpenRefine team is seeking a junior developer who will build the Wikimedia-specific features, as web services hosted on <a href="https://wikitech.wikimedia.org/wiki/Portal:Toolforge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Toolforge</a> or <a href="https://wikitech.wikimedia.org/wiki/Portal:Cloud_VPS" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Cloud VPS</a> for the abovementioned functionalities. </p><ul><li>This is a part time contract, over a period of 6 months.</li><li>Active work will be around 20 weeks, roughly from September 2021 until end February 2022.</li><li>For an average of 20 hours per week.</li><li>Fully remote. We encourage developers from outside of the USA and EU to apply.</li><li>We have between 14,000 USD and 16,000 USD available to complete this assignment, depending on experience. The payment details will be negotiated with the contractor, who will invoice Code for Science &amp; Society for their work towards the corresponding goals.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="responsibilities">Responsibilities<a class="hash-link" href="#responsibilities" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The Junior Developer:</p><ul><li>Develops a new OpenRefine reconciliation service specifically for Wikimedia Commons, inspired by the existing <a href="https://wikidata.reconci.link/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata Reconciliation Service</a> and following the <a href="https://reconciliation-api.github.io/specs/latest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reconciliation Service API Protocol</a>.</li><li>Develops a batch upload tool for <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Structured_data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">structured data on Wikimedia Commons</a>. Depending on circumstances, this batch upload functionality will be developed to be compatible with already existing upload tools in the Wikimedia ecosystem, such as <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Help:QuickStatements" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QuickStatements</a>, or as a new tool.</li><li>Works in close collaboration with their colleague (OpenRefine developer), and will regularly coordinate with the product manager and the rest of the OpenRefine development team.</li></ul><p>You can read more about this project, the planned tasks and the various roles, in the <a href="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:Project/Structured_Data_on_Wikimedia_Commons_functionalities_in_OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">public grant proposal</a> on meta.wikimedia.org.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="qualifications">Qualifications<a class="hash-link" href="#qualifications" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please do not self-censor if you do not meet all of these criteria, as you will develop your skills during the project.</p><ul><li>Experience developing web services in a language of your choice.</li><li>Enthusiasm for writing good documentation and tests alongside your code.</li><li>Ability to work independently in a fully remote project.</li><li>Experience with open source development workflows on GitHub.</li><li>Familiarity with tool deployment on the Wikimedia Toolforge.</li><li>Familiarity or experience with datasets in non-Western languages, non-Latin scripts, right to left writing systems, non-Western calendars, etc. is a plus.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-respond">How to respond<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-respond" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Please send your resume or CV, sample of your relevant previous work, and a short letter of interest to <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org.</a> We will schedule an interview with short-listed candidates. Applications will be reviewed on a rolling basis, with an aim to fill the position by July 30.</p><p><em>OpenRefine is fiscally sponsored by Code for Science and Society (CS&amp;S). CS&amp;S is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization thereby creating a culture that allows us to better serve our clientele, our employees and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our colleagues and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one’s employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sandra Fauconnier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing our new user manual]]></title>
        <id>/2021/07/07/hiring-commons</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/07/07/hiring-commons"/>
        <updated>2021-07-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The OpenRefine team is delighted to share our new user manual!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The OpenRefine team is delighted to share <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our new user manual</a>!</p><p>This reference covers every aspect of the tool, from installation to exporting a cleaned dataset.</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/2021-user-manual.png" alt="A screenshot of the new user manual." class="img_ev3q"></p><p>At this point we would like to hear from you: Does this new user manual help you? Did we cover everything you'd expect? Any suggestions to make it better?</p><p>We're looking for your feedback on every aspect: the structure, the text, the design, the images, and anything we've missed. We'd especially love to hear from you if you're a new user and are using this manual to install and run OpenRefine for the first time.</p><p>We recommend that you start by <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/manual/installing#installing-or-upgrading" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">following along with the user manual</a> to <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/releases/tag/3.4.1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">install or upgrade to the latest version of OpenRefine: version 3.4.1</a>.
Then, try out some tasks alongside the relevant sections of the user manual. Don't try to read the whole thing - just focus on sections that are most important to you.</p><p>If you'd like to share your thoughts:</p><ul><li>Please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/4KkoJFpSrWDMkrh6A" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our feedback form</a>. This helps us be sure we're hearing from a broad range of participants. Please fill out the form even if you don't have much to say - we'd love to know if you've taken a look regardless. There is space within the form to report specific requested changes and line edits, as well as give us your general impression.</li><li>You can also suggest edits directly on GitHub (use the "Edit this page" link at the end of each page of the <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">new docs</a>). This will create a pull request with your suggestions; this requires a GitHub account.</li></ul><p>We're also asking people who have written tutorials, who give workshops, and who share links on their websites to update those links to point to <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">docs.openrefine.org</a>.
While the documentation will always be open to improvements, this is now the authoritative source for information about the tool's functions and features. We will eventually be deleting old pages from the <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wiki on Github</a>. </p><p>If you're the author of a tutorial, we will try to get in touch soon to talk to you about updating your documentation online. If you don't hear from us, please reach out! We'd love to chat about the new docs.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Allana Mayer</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing our new user manual]]></title>
        <id>/2021/01/26/announcing-our-new-user-manual</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2021/01/26/announcing-our-new-user-manual"/>
        <updated>2021-01-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The OpenRefine team is delighted to share our new user manual!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The OpenRefine team is delighted to share <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our new user manual</a>!</p><p>This reference covers every aspect of the tool, from installation to exporting a cleaned dataset.</p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://openrefine.org/images/2021-user-manual.png" alt="A screenshot of the new user manual." class="img_ev3q"></p><p>At this point we would like to hear from you: Does this new user manual help you? Did we cover everything you'd expect? Any suggestions to make it better?</p><p>We're looking for your feedback on every aspect: the structure, the text, the design, the images, and anything we've missed. We'd especially love to hear from you if you're a new user and are using this manual to install and run OpenRefine for the first time.</p><p>We recommend that you start by <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/manual/installing#installing-or-upgrading" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">following along with the user manual</a> to <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/releases/tag/3.4.1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">install or upgrade to the latest version of OpenRefine: version 3.4.1</a>.
Then, try out some tasks alongside the relevant sections of the user manual. Don't try to read the whole thing - just focus on sections that are most important to you.</p><p>If you'd like to share your thoughts:</p><ul><li>Please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/4KkoJFpSrWDMkrh6A" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our feedback form</a>. This helps us be sure we're hearing from a broad range of participants. Please fill out the form even if you don't have much to say - we'd love to know if you've taken a look regardless. There is space within the form to report specific requested changes and line edits, as well as give us your general impression.</li><li>You can also suggest edits directly on GitHub (use the "Edit this page" link at the end of each page of the <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">new docs</a>). This will create a pull request with your suggestions; this requires a GitHub account.</li></ul><p>We're also asking people who have written tutorials, who give workshops, and who share links on their websites to update those links to point to <a href="https://docs.openrefine.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">docs.openrefine.org</a>.
While the documentation will always be open to improvements, this is now the authoritative source for information about the tool's functions and features. We will eventually be deleting old pages from the <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wiki on Github</a>. </p><p>If you're the author of a tutorial, we will try to get in touch soon to talk to you about updating your documentation online. If you don't hear from us, please reach out! We'd love to chat about the new docs.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Allana Mayer</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Call for Proposals: Improving the Contributor Experience in OpenRefine]]></title>
        <id>/2020/08/28/cfp-contributor-experience</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/08/28/cfp-contributor-experience"/>
        <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine is a power tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than 10 years, and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://openrefine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine</a> is a power tool to clean messy data, popular in a diverse range of communities. It has been serving the needs of journalists, librarians, Wikipedians, scientists for more than 10 years, and is taught in many curricula and workshops around the world.</p><p>The OpenRefine advisory committee solicits proposals to improve contributor onboarding and retention in the project, funded by a grant from the <a href="https://www.siliconvalleycf.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silicon Valley Community Foundation</a> via the <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a> under their <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science</a> programme.</p><p>OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501<!-- -->(<!-- -->c<!-- -->)<!-- -->(3) charitable organization in the US.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="scope">Scope<a class="hash-link" href="#scope" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We solicit proposals to improve the day-to-day experience of OpenRefine contributors. This covers the following areas:</p><ul><li><strong>Documentation for contributors.</strong> This can cover a wide range of topics, such as IDE setup instructions, testing guidelines, code style, pull request process, documentation of the overall architecture of the code base, guide to debugging, guide to extension development, translation workflow, release process, or other similar areas.</li><li><strong>Testing improvements.</strong> We currently do not have any UI testing in place, our code coverage for the backend is very sparse, and we do not have wide-ranging integration tests either. Proposals to improve our testing are therefore in scope as well.</li><li><strong>Tackling technical debt.</strong> This can cover migration out of unmaintained or obsolete libraries,  dependency management, continuous integration and other housekeeping tasks.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="timeline-and-process">Timeline and Process<a class="hash-link" href="#timeline-and-process" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We will used a community centered process to ensure that decisions on technical direction are agreed upon by the community. </p><ul><li>28 August 2020: Call for proposals announced and mailing list is open for project submissions and discussion</li><li>21 September 2020: Proposals due, open discussion period ends, and advisory committee discusses proposals and makes decisions on priorities and budgets</li><li>30 September 2020: Selected projects announced and contracts established with CS&amp;S to complete the work</li><li>15 October 2020: Earliest work start date</li><li>30 April 2021: Latest work end date</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="budget">Budget<a class="hash-link" href="#budget" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We have 50,000 USD available to fund these projects. Selected proposals will invoice Code for Science &amp; Society for their work towards the corresponding goals.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-apply">How to apply<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-apply" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>You do not need to have a fully formed idea to submit to the mailing list. The community and OpenRefine Advisory Committee will help you develop and scope your work. We have added a template so you can see the parts of a finished scope of work, but you do not need to know what the timeline and budget will be to propose an idea.</p><ul><li>Propose your project on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/openrefine-dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">openrefine-dev@googlegroups.com</a> mailing list, to build  consensus around it and refine the scope of your work with input from the community. We invite open discussion on all submitted proposals on the mailing list.</li><li>Submit a proposal to <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org</a> for the work you intend to carry out, including a timeline and budget (see template below). If you have not yet contributed to OpenRefine, please also include a short portfolio demonstrating your work in other projects;</li><li>Approved projects will sign a contract for the work with CS&amp;S;</li><li>The contributor will invoice CS&amp;S according to the payment schedule agreed to with OpenRefine </li></ul><p>Projects will be selected on the basis of their estimated benefit to the community of contributors, their cost and the contribution record of the proposer (in OpenRefine or similar projects).</p><p><em>Code for Science &amp; Society is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization, creating a culture that allows us to better serve our projects, our employees, and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our employees and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one’s employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="application-template">Application template<a class="hash-link" href="#application-template" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><strong>Project title:</strong> Improving OpenRefine development with Foobar</p><p><strong>Project description (about 250 words):</strong> "I feel that the lack of Foobar has really impeded my work on the project so far. Currently we just have some Barfoo integration, but this tool is abandoned and does not work well on Windows. There seems to be consensus in the community for using Foobar 4, which would be added in the repository. We would make sure its integration with IntelliJ and Eclipse work well. The bulk of the task is to convert the existing Barfoo files to Foobar's format. (...)" Please describe why this work is important and an overview of how you approach solving this problem.  </p><p><strong>Mailing list thread:</strong> Give a link to the openrefine-dev thread where your proposal was discussed.</p><p><strong>Key milestones:</strong> Please break down the work you want to do into small chunks with defined checkpoints (ie: I will do X, and we will know when it is done because an X will appear on the screen)</p><p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Is this a 4 week sprint? A 3 month project? Break down how long the work will take.</p><p><strong>Budget:</strong> Please estimate the cost of this work and include the cost of any additional services you will need to use.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to our 2020 Google Summer of Code and Outreachy interns]]></title>
        <id>/2020/05/04/outreachy-gsoc-projects</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/05/04/outreachy-gsoc-projects"/>
        <updated>2020-05-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce that three interns will join the development team this summer:]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce that three interns will join the development team this summer:</p><ul><li><p>Lisa Chandra (<a href="https://github.com/lisa761" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@lisa761</a>), Google Summer of Code intern, will improve our grid view by adding support for infinite scrolling (displaying the entire grid without the need to browse it by small pages). She is supervised by
Owen Stephens and Antonin Delpeuch.</p></li><li><p>Lu Liu (<a href="https://github.com/afkbrb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@afkbrb</a>), Google Summer of Code intern, will add support for OAuth and other Wikibase instances in the Wikidata extension. He will be supervised by Tom Morris and Antonin Delpeuch.</p></li><li><p>Ekta Mishra (<a href="https://github.com/darecoder1999" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@darecoder1999</a>), our Outreachy intern, will work on improving the quality assurance features of the Wikidata integration, by adding support for new Wikidata constraints and improving the existing
functionality. She will be supervised by Antonin Delpeuch.</p></li></ul><p>We are very excited to welcome them to the team and are looking forward to working with them. The Google Summer of Code internships will run from June 1 to August 24 and the Outreachy internship from May 19 to August 18.</p><p>We thank all applicants for the quality of their proposals and their contributions to the project earlier this year.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Help us write OpenRefine's new documentation]]></title>
        <id>/2020/04/23/documentation-hire</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/04/23/documentation-hire"/>
        <updated>2020-04-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The OpenRefine team is seeking a technical writer to help write a reference manual for the tool. This is a 6 months contract, funded by a grant from the Silicon Valley Community Foundation via the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative under their Essential Open Source Software for Science programme.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The OpenRefine team is seeking a technical writer to help write a reference manual for the tool. This is a 6 months contract, funded by a grant from the <a href="https://www.siliconvalleycf.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silicon Valley Community Foundation</a> via the <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a> under their <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science</a> programme.</p><p>OpenRefine is a fiscally sponsored project of <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science &amp; Society Inc</a>, a 501<!-- -->(<!-- -->c<!-- -->)<!-- -->(3) charitable organization in the US.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="experience">Experience<a class="hash-link" href="#experience" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We are looking for one or more enthusiastic contributors to join our fully remote team, to help us write a reference manual for OpenRefine. The following skills are key:</p><ul><li>Ability to write documentation fluently in English. Experience with writing software documentation is ideal but not necessary;</li><li>Experience with OpenRefine as a user and ideally as a trainer (writing tutorials, running workshops or developing any other training material);</li><li>Familiarity with <a href="https://github.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a>, as documentation changes will be reviewed there, and much of our project planning is also happening there. Our documentation is written in <a href="https://guides.github.com/features/mastering-markdown/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Markdown</a>, for which there exists many visual editors (for instance, <a href="https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/docs_to_markdown/700168918607" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">plugins to export from Google Docs to Markdown</a>, or the <a href="https://hackmd.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HackMD online editor</a>).</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="overview-of-the-work">Overview of the work<a class="hash-link" href="#overview-of-the-work" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>As part of <a href="http://openrefine.org/images/czi-eoss-proposal.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our milestones for the EOSS grant</a>, we are in the process of migrating our existing documentation from <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our GitHub Wiki</a> to a dedicated documentation platform. This effort is described in our root planning document and coordinated by Owen Stephens and Antonin Delpeuch. We have identified multiple documentation areas:</p><ul><li><strong>Product reference</strong>, documenting for users all the features offered by the tool in a systematic fashion;</li><li><strong>Technical reference</strong>, aimed at developers, explaining the architecture of the tool;</li><li><strong>Project documentation</strong>, aimed at anyone who wants to contribute code, translations, documentation, user support around OpenRefine;</li><li><strong>Tutorials and how-to guides</strong>, showing by example how the tool can be used for specific data cleaning problems;</li><li><strong>Discussions</strong>, to support users with their specific issues.</li></ul><p>You will be working on the <strong>product reference</strong> only. The goal for this documentation is to provide a thorough and systematic description of the behaviour of all user-facing features of the tool, such as:</p><ul><li>Operations</li><li>Importers</li><li>Exporters</li><li>GREL functions</li><li>Facets</li><li>Bundled extensions such as Jython and the Wikidata integration</li></ul><p>This reference documentation is meant to support users in their exploration of the tool. Users will typically discover the tool through existing tutorials or workshops: these introductory training materials can refer to the product documentation to help users dive deeper in the concepts demonstrated by the course.</p><p>The product reference will be written in Markdown using <a href="https://docusaurus.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Docusaurus</a>. Documentation for a sample operation is provided as an example of what we are aiming for:</p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.openrefine.org/operations/key_value_columnize.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rendered version</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/blob/master/docs/src/operations/key_value_columnize.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Markdown source</a></li></ul><p>Your task will be to write similar documentation for other functions of the tool.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="compensation-and-timeline">Compensation and timeline<a class="hash-link" href="#compensation-and-timeline" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We have 25,000 USD available to complete these milestones. The payment details will be negotiated with the contractor(s).</p><p>The work could be done by a single individual or by a team, depending on the availability of applicants.</p><p>We are aiming to hire one or more technical writers for this task by the end of May 2020.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-respond">How to respond<a class="hash-link" href="#how-to-respond" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><strong>Update (2020-05-18):</strong> the application period for this position has lapsed, thank you to everyone who got in touch. We will announce the results in the coming weeks.</p><p>Please send your resume or CV, sample of your relevant previous work and a short letter of interest to <a href="mailto:advisory.committee@openrefine.org." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">advisory.committee@openrefine.org.</a> We will schedule an interview with short-listed candidates.</p><p><em>Code for Science &amp; Society is an equal opportunity employer committed to hiring a diverse workforce at all levels of the organization, creating a culture that allows us to better serve our projects, our employees, and our communities. We value and encourage the contributions of our employees and strive to create an environment where everyone can reach their full potential and drive outstanding results. All qualified applicants will receive consideration for employment without regard to race, national origin, age, sex, religion, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, veteran status, gender identity or expression, or any other basis protected by local, state, or federal law. This policy applies with regard to all aspects of one’s employment, including hiring, transfer, promotion, compensation, eligibility for benefits, and termination.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outreachy and Google Summer of Code]]></title>
        <id>/2020/02/22/outreachy-gsoc</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/02/22/outreachy-gsoc"/>
        <updated>2020-02-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine will offer internships via the Outreachy and Google Summer of Code programs this year.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenRefine will offer internships via the <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Outreachy</a> and <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Summer of Code</a> programs this year.</p><p>For Outreachy, pre-applications are still open and <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/apply/project-selection/#openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our proposed projects</a> will be revealed on March 5th.</p><p>For the Google Summer of Code, check out <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/5904592325312512/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our organization page</a> and our <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/GSoC-2020%C2%A0Ideas" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">project ideas</a>.</p><p>We are short of mentors - if you want to help with mentoring students for the Google Summer of Code, do add yourself to the project ideas (on existing projects or on additional ones).</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2020 survey results]]></title>
        <id>/2020/02/20/ 2020-survey-results</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/02/20/ 2020-survey-results"/>
        <updated>2020-02-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The results of our fourth OpenRefine user survey are out! We received 178 responses in less than four weeks (vs. 122 in 2018 over seven months)! The goal of the study is to keep an accurate and up to date picture of the OpenRefine community. When possible, we compared the 2020 results with our previous survey. You can view the full details of the 2012, 2014, and 2018 surveys]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The results of our fourth OpenRefine user survey are out! We received 178 responses in less than four weeks (vs. 122 in 2018 over seven months)! The goal of the study is to keep an accurate and up to date picture of the OpenRefine community. When possible, we compared the 2020 results with our previous survey. You can view the full details of the <a href="http://googlerefine.blogspot.ca/2012/10/google-refine-usage-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2012</a>, <a href="http://openrefine.org/blog/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2014</a>, and <a href="http://openrefine.org/blog/2018/07/16/2018-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2018</a> surveys</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-you-identify-with">Community you identify with<a class="hash-link" href="#community-you-identify-with" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>While librarians remain the largest group (37.64%), Wikidata contributor (and semantic web users - 12.92%) made an entry as the second-largest user group in 2020! Researchers now rank third with 10.7% of the user base. Note the community Archivist was not suggested in the answer but still gather 4.49% of the answer! </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/1.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/1.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-often-do-you-use-openrefine">How often do you use OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-often-do-you-use-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Usage frequency remains globally the same since 2012, with about a third using OpenRefine weekly, a third using it monthly, and a third using it less than once per month. Note that we did not offer the option <em>Less than once a month</em> in the 2012 survey and remove the First time user option after 2012.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/21.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/21.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine">For how long have you been using OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Users with over two years of experience keep growing years over the years and now 57% of the user base (vs. 51% in 2018). We take it as a positive fact where we can keep our user base while being able to attract new users. </p><p>Note that in the below analysis, we included users that never used OpenRefine in the less than six months group (five respondents in 2014, nine in 2018, three in 2020). </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/23.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/23.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-will-you-rate-your-skills-using-openrefine">How will you rate your skills using OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-will-you-rate-your-skills-using-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In all our previous surveys, we asked respondents to rate their skills from one to five. One being a novice in Refine and five being a master. The number of novice respondents dropped in 2020 from 16% to 7%. The skills level is related to the frequency of usage and not to the years of experience. No matter how long you have been using GREL, you got to practice it every day to improve!</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/24.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/24.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="version-of-openrefine">Version of OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#version-of-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>While the majority are using the latest stable version at the time of the survey (OpenRefine 3.2)</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/3.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/3.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="high-level-tasks-you-do-with-openrefine">High-level tasks you do with OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#high-level-tasks-you-do-with-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Usage breakdown remains stable compared to the 2012 and 2018 survey. With two notables differences: </p><ul><li>Preparing data to load into another system ranks now second with over 73% of the respondents (vs. 66% in 2018)</li><li>Now more than half of the OpenRefine users use the reconciliation feature (44% in 2018 to 54% in 2020).</li><li>We see a net decrease in OpenRefine for data discovery (understand data you don't own) or preparing for data visualization. </li></ul><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/4.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/4.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondents can select multiple answers. Click on the image to enlarge it.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="do-you-use-plugin-or-extension">Do you use plugin or extension?<a class="hash-link" href="#do-you-use-plugin-or-extension" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>72% of the respondents do not use plugins or extension; 11% installed only one plugin, and 17% of them installed more than one. Overall we see a drop in usage for many plugins.</p><p>The top three plugins are: </p><ul><li>RDF extension - by DERI - 19.7%</li><li>Named-Entity Recognition - by Ruben Verborgh (Free Your Metadata) - 13.9%</li><li>History tools, cross cell tools, pivot tool and scatterplot tool using D3 - by VIB-BITS - 10.9%</li></ul><p>The DBpedia extension has not been updated for seven years, but its usage grew from 5.7% two years ago to 10.9% in 2020. The usage of DBpedia is not linked to any particular community (6 librarians, 3 for-profits, 2 archivists, and one for cultural heritage, data scientist, researcher and wikidata contributor). Any explanation is welcome!</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/5.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/5.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondents can select multiple answers. We consolidated the 41 blank answers with <em>I don't use plugin or extension</em>. Click on the image to enlarge it.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="do-you-use-a-reconciliation-service">Do you use a reconciliation service?<a class="hash-link" href="#do-you-use-a-reconciliation-service" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In 2020, close to 65% of OpenRefine users connect to a reconciliation service! This is massive progress from 48% two years ago! 26.52% of the respondents use more than one service versus 18.03% in 2018.</p><p>While Wikidata (45%) and VIAF (22%) dominate the list, we see new services not listed in 2018:</p><ul><li>GND (six respondents)</li><li>Getty Vocabularies (three respondents)</li><li>in-house reconciliation service (three respondents)</li><li>Open Library (one respondent)</li><li>ORCID (one respondent)</li><li>Organized Crime and Corruption Reporting Project (one respondent)</li><li>Planning to use with Linked Data Finland's datasets (one respondent)</li><li>Sharedshelf Built Work Registry Reconciliation Service (one respondent)</li><li>SNAC (one respondent)</li><li>Nomisma (one respondent)</li></ul><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/6.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/6.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondents can select multiple answers. Click on the image to enlarge it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="perception-of-refine">Perception of Refine:<a class="hash-link" href="#perception-of-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The following word clouds are more eye-pleasing than an in-depth analysis.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-did-you-choose-openrefine-which-features">Why did you choose OpenRefine (Which features)<a class="hash-link" href="#why-did-you-choose-openrefine-which-features" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Wikidata makes a nice entry on the list!</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/reason.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/reason.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternative-tools">Alternative tools<a class="hash-link" href="#alternative-tools" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Excel, R, python and Google Sheets remain the mains alternative to OpenRefine. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/alternative.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/alternative.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="word-used-to-describe-openrefine">Word used to describe OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#word-used-to-describe-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The most common expressions to describe OpenRefine are "Excel on steroid" and "a data cleaning tool."</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/describe.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2020survey/describe.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="from-the-feature-request-and-anything-to-add">From the Feature Request and Anything to add<a class="hash-link" href="#from-the-feature-request-and-anything-to-add" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>We compiled below suggestions and feature requests submitted via the survey. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="features-request">Features Request<a class="hash-link" href="#features-request" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Improve performance and support larger dataset  (7 requests) - this is on the 2020 roadmap and under development on the 4.x branch!</li><li>Better UX (6 requests)</li><li>Online support with user login and permission (4 requests)</li><li>Make regex expression easier to build (4 requests)</li><li>An easier installation process, potentially with a standalone java (4 requests)</li><li>List in OpenRefine all plugins available (4 requests) </li><li>List in OpenRefine all the reconciliation service available (3 requests)</li><li>Better support for hierarchical data (2 requests)</li><li>Allow to memory from the front end (2 requests)</li><li>Would let me choose where I can store my files!</li><li>Have real Title Case transforms that left articles like A, An, And, The lowercased as well as prepositions instead of capitalizing each word.</li><li>Add row to a project</li><li>Support POST request</li><li>Ability to save facet</li><li>Allow extensions to be written in python. </li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="wikidata-related">Wikidata Related<a class="hash-link" href="#wikidata-related" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Support editing and uploading to  Structured Data on Commons: see ticket <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/2144" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#2144</a>, and external Wikibases (2 requests)</li><li>Better error handling when uploading to Wikidata (2 requests)</li><li>Had improved Wikidata integration, particularly more control over modifying existing statements including qualifiers and references</li><li>Support wikicode</li><li>Build automated Wikidata ingest pipelines</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="improve-history">Improve History<a class="hash-link" href="#improve-history" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We received three separate requests to improve the history in the way described in our roadmap. </p><p>Respondents asked for an easier way to edit/tweak operation history (i.e. adjust an edit made multiple steps ago without losing subsequent steps). It would be nice if cell provenance could be accessed programmatically or via the interface. So, for instance, in terms of rewinding to a certain state, it would be nice to know at what step a cell/row/column last changed, or what the previous state of the cell/row/column was, or what the state was at a particular step.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="plugin-to-support-in-core">Plugin to support in core<a class="hash-link" href="#plugin-to-support-in-core" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>RDF (6 requests)</li><li>csv reconcile (5 requests). See ticket <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/2003" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#2003</a> and part of <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/GSoC-2020%C2%A0Ideas#reconciliation-server-within-openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Summer of Code 2020 proposal</a></li><li>Vib-bits (3 requests)</li><li>NER (3 requests)</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="training">Training<a class="hash-link" href="#training" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Make OpenRefine better known (5 requests)</li><li>Make GREL more accessible. Possibly with more contextual help or a GREL-formula builder (3 requests)</li><li>Provide more documentation on how to use reconciliation services and the different plugins (3 requests)</li><li>Improve the onboarding.</li><li>Provide more workshop and training on OpenRefine</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine joins Code for Science and Society]]></title>
        <id>/2020/01/31/css</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2020/01/31/css"/>
        <updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As announced in the previous post, the OpenRefine project has joined Code for Science and Society as a Sponsored Project.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As announced in the previous post, the OpenRefine project has joined <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science and Society</a> as a Sponsored Project.
We are thrilled to join this new home, which will help the project grow on the long term and set its openness in stone.</p><p>This is the occasion for us to improve our gouvernance model, with the creation of two committees.
The advisory committee runs the project on a day to day basis and is composed of Martin Magdinier, Thad Guidry and Antonin Delpeuch.
The steering committee oversees the general direction of the project and initates links with other organizations and projects. We
are proud of our all-star line up for this steering committee, in alphabetical order:</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/christopher-erdmann-1213a456" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chris Erdmann</a> (<a href="https://renci.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">University of North Carolina, RENCI</a>)</p></li><li><p>Alicia Fagerving (<a href="https://wikimedia.se/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Sverige</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://wikimediafoundation.org/profile/sandra-fauconnier/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sandra Fauconnier</a> (<a href="https://wikimediafoundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikimedia Foundation</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://rufuspollock.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rufus Pollock</a> (<a href="https://datopian.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Datopian</a>, <a href="https://okfn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Open Knowledge Foundation</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/smfrogers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Simon Rogers</a> (<a href="https://newsinitiative.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google News Initiative</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://lozanarossenova.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lozana Rossenova</a> (<a href="https://rhizome.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rhizome</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/juliane-schneider-4a06535/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Juliane Schneider</a> (<a href="https://catalyst.harvard.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harvard Catalyst, Clinical and Translational Science Center</a>)</p></li><li><p>Wesley Sherperd (<a href="http://unifydinsights.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Unifyd Insights</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://github.com/Blakko" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fabio Tacchelli</a> (<a href="https://siren.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Siren Solutions</a>)</p></li><li><p><a href="https://rubenverborgh.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ruben Verborgh</a> (<a href="http://www.ugent.be/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">University of Ghent</a>)</p></li></ul><p>Thank you all for joining us in this exciting adventure!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine funded by the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative as an Essential Open Source Software for Science]]></title>
        <id>/2019/11/14/czi-eoss</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2019/11/14/czi-eoss"/>
        <updated>2019-11-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are pleased to announce that the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative (CZI) has awarded OpenRefine a $200,000 grant to fund its development in 2020.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce that the <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chan Zuckerberg Initiative</a> (CZI) has awarded OpenRefine a $200,000 grant to fund its development in 2020.
This award is part of CZI’s <a href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Essential Open Source Software for Science program</a> which awarded $5 million to over 40 projects.</p><p>This grant will be used towards two main objectives:</p><ul><li>grow the community of OpenRefine contributors by reaching out to seasoned users and helping them get involved more closely in the project.</li><li>revamp the core architecture of the tool to handle larger datasets and improve workflows.</li></ul><p>This is the occasion for the project to join <a href="https://codeforscience.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Code for Science and Society</a>'s Sponsored Project Program. We will follow up with another post about that when this is finalized.</p><p><a href="http://www.meanboyfriend.com/overdue_ideas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Owen Stephens</a> and <a href="http://antonin.delpeuch.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Antonin Delpeuch</a> will be hired to work towards these goals, with the help of additional contractors for specific subtasks.
For more details about our plans, see our <a href="http://openrefine.org/images/czi-eoss-proposal.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">grant proposal</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[WikidataCon Award 2019]]></title>
        <id>/2019/11/02/wikidatacon-award</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2019/11/02/wikidatacon-award"/>
        <updated>2019-11-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are pleased to announce that the Wikidata community has awarded a WikidataCon 2019 Award to OpenRefine in]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce that the <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Main_Page" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata</a> community has awarded a <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:OpenRefine_WikidataCon_Award_winner.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WikidataCon 2019 Award</a> to OpenRefine in
the <emph>Editing</emph> category.</p><p><a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Tools/OpenRefine/Editing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata editing with OpenRefine</a> was introduced in version 3.0, released in September 2018. It was used since to perform millions of Wikidata edits, either <a href="https://tools.wmflabs.org/editgroups/?tool=OR" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">directly from OpenRefine</a> or via <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Help:QuickStatements" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QuickStatements</a>.</p><p>This award goes to all our users who do the hard work behind these imports, the mentors who organize workshops around the tool or write training material around it, the developers and translators, and the <a href="https://newsinitiative.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google News Initiative</a> which funded this feature.</p><p>For a 10 minutes introduction to Wikidata editing with OpenRefine, we recommend this video tutorial by Emma Carroll (who deserves special thanks for its clarity):</p><div class="video-wrapper"><iframe width="500" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wfS1qTKFQoI" frameborder="0"> </iframe></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Antonin Delpeuch</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2018 survey results]]></title>
        <id>/2018/07/16/ 2018-survey-results</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2018/07/16/ 2018-survey-results"/>
        <updated>2018-07-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[From December 12, 2017, to June 7, 2018, we ran our third OpenRefine user survey.  Over five months; we received 122 responses. The goal of the study is to keep an accurate and up to date picture of the OpenRefine community. When possible, we compared the 2018 results with our previous survey. You can view the full details of the 2012 and 2014 surveys.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From December 12, 2017, to June 7, 2018, we ran our third OpenRefine user survey.  Over five months; we received 122 responses. The goal of the study is to keep an accurate and up to date picture of the OpenRefine community. When possible, we compared the 2018 results with our previous survey. You can view the full details of the <a href="http://googlerefine.blogspot.ca/2012/10/google-refine-usage-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2012</a> and <a href="http://openrefine.org/blog/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2014</a> surveys.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-you-identify-with">Community you identify with<a class="hash-link" href="#community-you-identify-with" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Librarians and researchers remain the two largest user group with 28.69%  and 15.57% of the respondents (which is consistent with the 2014 results). We can notice the Data Science, and Non-Profit organization groups increased since 2014.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/1.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/1.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-often-do-you-use-openrefine">How often do you use OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-often-do-you-use-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Usage frequency remains globally the same since 2012, with fewer respondents using it weekly (34.4% vs. 41% in 2014) and more on a monthly basis (42% today vs. 30% in 2014). </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/21.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/21.png" class="inset"></a><p>The user base change from daily users to weekly or monthly users. Note that we did not offer the option <em>Less than once a month</em> in the 2012 survey and remove the First time user option after 2012. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/22.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/22.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine">For how long have you been using OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Users with over two years of experience are now representing 50% of the user base (vs. 38% in 2014). If we compare to the previous year, we see mostly the drop in user with less than six months of experience. While we cannot provide a reason for the decline, we can suppose it is due to the survey methodology, the maturity of the self-service data preparation markets with alternative tools available to the users or because fewer people have been introduced to OpenRefine over the last year. </p><p>Note that in the below analysis we included users that never used OpenRefine in the less than six months group (five respondents in 2014, nine in 2018). </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/23.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/23.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-will-you-rate-your-skills-using-openrefine">How will you rate your skills using OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-will-you-rate-your-skills-using-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Both in 2012 and 2014 we asked respondents to rate their skills from one to five. One being a novice in Refine and five being a master. This graph confirms the trends that the community is composed of advanced users with the only a third of them rating their skills at 1 or 2 out of 5.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/24.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/24.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="version-of-openrefine">Version of OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#version-of-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The majority of the respondents use the latest release of OpenRefine (2.8).</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/3.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/3.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="high-level-tasks-you-do-with-openrefine">High-level tasks you do with OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#high-level-tasks-you-do-with-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Usage breakdown remains stable compared to the 2012 survey. 87.77% of the respondents are using OpenRefine to address more than one type of task.</p><p>The majority of the respondents use OpenRefine to normalize data (80%) and transform it (75%).  We introduced the answer <em>Preparing a dataset before visualization in another application (R, D3, Tableau, Fusion Table ...)</em>  in the 2018 survey.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/4.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/4.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondant can select multiple answer. Click on the image to enlarge it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="do-you-use-plugin-or-extension">Do you use plugin or extension?<a class="hash-link" href="#do-you-use-plugin-or-extension" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>62.3% of the respondents do not use plugins or extension; 22.13% installed only one plugin and 15% of them installed more than one (with one person installing eight plugins!). The RDF extension is the most popular extension with 14.8% of the respondents using it, followed by the VIB BITS and NER plugins.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/5.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/5.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondent can select multiple answers. We consolidated blank answer with I don't use plugin or extension. Click on the image to enlarge it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="do-you-use-a-reconciliation-service">Do you use a reconciliation service?<a class="hash-link" href="#do-you-use-a-reconciliation-service" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The two top services used are Wikidata and reconcile-csv. 30.33% of the respondent installed only one reconciliation when 18.03% used more than one (with one person using six services!), and 51.6% of them do not use a reconciliation service. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/6.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/6.png" class="inset"></a><p>Note: Respondent can select multiple answers. Click on the image to enlarge it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="perception-of-refine">Perception of Refine:<a class="hash-link" href="#perception-of-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The following word clouds are more eye-pleasing than an in-depth analysis.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-did-you-choose-openrefine-which-features">Why did you choose OpenRefine (Which features)<a class="hash-link" href="#why-did-you-choose-openrefine-which-features" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/reason.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/reason.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternative-tools">Alternative tools<a class="hash-link" href="#alternative-tools" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Excel, R, and python remain the mains alternative to OpenRefine. Since 2014, we can notice the emergence of other self-service data preparation tools like Trifacta and Talend Data Preparation. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/alternative.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/alternative.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="word-used-to-describe-openrefine">Word used to describe OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#word-used-to-describe-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/describe.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018survey/describe.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="from-the-feature-request-and-anything-to-add">From the Feature Request and Anything to add<a class="hash-link" href="#from-the-feature-request-and-anything-to-add" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>We compiled below suggestions and feature requests submitted via the survey. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="features-request">Features Request:<a class="hash-link" href="#features-request" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Improve performance and support larger dataset (11 requests)</li><li>Improve GREL documentation with more snippets, recipe to help users to write GREL (5 requests).</li><li>Support a library of GREL expression to save common transform (convert date, names, common regex, geocode data) with a native button to call them (5 requests).</li><li>Hosted version (4 requests) for collaboration (2 requests).</li><li>Improvement of the batch mode (3 requests) including details on which clustering process its done with its parameters. </li><li>Support for Spark, Apache arrow/parquet.</li><li>Detect the nature of the information based on a pattern (ex: column x contains phone numbers) and check if values in a field are acceptable or exist in locally controlled vocabularies.</li><li>Store the templates for export in other formats like XML.</li><li>Improve python support (store functions; auto-indent code).</li><li>Better manage XML and JSON files.</li><li>Export result to clipboard.</li><li>An option to stop the service from the interface. </li><li>Easier configuration memory allocated to OpenRefine.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="gui">GUI<a class="hash-link" href="#gui" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Some suggestions regarding the User Interface:</p><ul><li>Renaming columns (2 requests) via all or double-clicking on them.</li><li>Moving columns by drag and drop (2 requests).</li><li>GREL Editors is too small for advanced GREL.</li><li>Project organization using a directory structure.</li><li>Search across all columns in a project.</li><li>In the history tab, tagging and brief descriptions of the code would help in their discovery.</li><li>Bigger/adjustable window for RDF skeleton in the RDF extension.</li></ul><p>Regarding the reconciliation process: </p><ul><li>Reconciliation question should be a checkbox, not a toggle.</li><li>Keep reconciliation data (-&gt; links) when transformations are made across a column, e.g., combining the entries of two columns into one, now reconciliation data gets lost.</li><li>Easily remove old reconciliation services.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-language-or-format-support">New language or format support<a class="hash-link" href="#new-language-or-format-support" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Respondent suggested OpenRefine support more format and languages including:</p><ul><li>R language.</li><li>OCR.</li><li>.mrc/.mrk files.</li><li>tde format export.</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Update: Google News Initiative and technical road map]]></title>
        <id>/2018/06/16/Update</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2018/06/16/Update"/>
        <updated>2018-06-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recent Progress]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="recent-progress">Recent Progress<a class="hash-link" href="#recent-progress" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="openrefine-28-and-30">OpenRefine 2.8 and 3.0<a class="hash-link" href="#openrefine-28-and-30" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>OpenRefine 3.0 Beta was <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/releases/tag/3.0-beta" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">released on May 27</a>. This is the second release with the support of <a href="https://newsinitiative.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google News Initiative</a> (see more details below) and includes several major enhancements including: </p><ul><li>Wikidata extension to reconcile, enrich and push data from/to Wikidata. See the <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Tools/OpenRefine/Editing/Tutorials/Video" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video tutorial</a> and <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:Tools/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikidata documentation</a> (2.8 and 3.0);</li><li>Support of <a href="https://frictionlessdata.io/data-packages/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Data package</a> metadata standards to describe and package a collection of data (3.0)</li><li>Improved metadata and tag system to ease project identification from OpenRefine homepage (2.8 and 3.0);<a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018-06-Update/metadata.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2018-06-Update/metadata.png" class="center"></a></li><li>Fix the connection with Google Drive to import (3.0);</li><li>Support of HTTP Header when sending a request (3.0);<a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018-06-Update/header.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2018-06-Update/header.png" class="center"></a></li><li>Create project from a database connection and generate INSERT INTO statement (3.0);<a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018-06-Update/db.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2018-06-Update/db.png" class="center"></a></li><li>Support split multivalued-cells by regex/special characters (2.8);</li><li><a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues?q=milestone%3A2.8+reconciliation+label%3Areconciliation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Several improvements of the reconciliation API</a> (2.8) ;</li><li>Documentation improvement on <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our wiki</a>;</li></ul><p>OpenRefine 3.0 is under beta, and we still have few bugs. If you want to use it please backup your workspace directory before installing and report any problems that you encounter.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-logo">New Logo<a class="hash-link" href="#new-logo" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018-06-Update/new-open-refine-512px.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2018-06-Update/new-open-refine-512px.png" class="center"></a><p>Google News Initiative helped to design a new logo for OpenRefine. You may have noticed the new logo on our <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub project</a>. We made it part of the 3.0 release, and we will update it on the website when the deployment of the new website layout occurs in the coming weeks. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="translations">Translations<a class="hash-link" href="#translations" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>OpenRefine 3.0 is fully translated into five languages and available in seven more with over 87% coverage! Thanks a lot to all the community members who help to localize OpenRefine in their language! You can help complete existing translations or start a new language via <a href="https://hosted.weblate.org/projects/openrefine/translations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Weblate</a>. See our <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Translate-OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Translate OpenRefine wiki page</a> for more details. </p><p>Translation available: </p><ul><li>English 100.0% translated</li><li>Italian 100.0% translated</li><li>Japanese 100.0% translated </li><li>French 100.0% translated </li><li>German 100.0% translated </li><li>Portuguese (Brazil) 98.1% translated </li><li>Filipino 97.3% translated </li><li>Cebuano 97.5% % translated</li><li>Tagalog 97.2% translated </li><li>Hungarian 95.3% translated </li><li>Russian 93.4% translated </li><li>Chinese 90.0% translated </li><li>Spanish 89.3% translated</li><li>Hebrew 87.7% translated </li><li>Romanian 6.7% translated</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="google-news-initiative-support">Google News Initiative Support<a class="hash-link" href="#google-news-initiative-support" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2018-06-Update/GoogleNewsInitiative.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2018-06-Update/GoogleNewsInitiative.png" class="center"></a><p>In December 2017, <a href="https://newsinitiative.withgoogle.com/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google News Initiative</a> offered USD 100,000 to support the development of OpenRefine as described in the document <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1UwoT1nFk9zwqSlH8rmqKPmiLS2Liw7-KM5HTKD2VVi8/edit#heading=h.z6ne0og04bp5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Phase 1</a> and <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1lK3LT9Llwxqv4NFSQO33UX-P3vD1MzYefv6YCtf6HHk/edit#heading=h.z6ne0og04bp5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Phase 2+3</a>. So far the funds have been used to finance the release of OpenRefine 2.8 and 3.0 (over 150 issues closed!) and covers expenses to present OpenRefine at the <a href="https://www.ire.org/conferences/nicar18/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NICAR 18</a> and <a href="https://ire.org/conferences/ire-2018/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">IRE 18</a> conferences.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="governance">Governance<a class="hash-link" href="#governance" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The <a href="https://github.com/orgs/OpenRefine/people" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine core team</a> is currently managing the funds via a private US company to get off the ground quickly. We know that the private US corporation is not a viable solution in the long term and we are currently under discussion to join <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Software Freedom Conservancy</a>.</p><p>As we begin to use Software Freedom Conservancy as the parent organization of OpenRefine Foundation, we will clarify and formalize our governance model. In the meanwhile, we welcome anyone feedbacks and comments via our GitHub project or our <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">user</a> and <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/openrefine-dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developer</a> mailing lists. If you would like to request financing for the development of a feature, the attendance or the organization of an event, please reach out via one of our mailing lists.</p><p>You can review our usage of the funds in the following <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/17hldPOw8W_TGM2DuKWbkFX-rexkQiE5esluZ8buadao/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Finance document.</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="openrefine-road-map">OpenRefine road map<a class="hash-link" href="#openrefine-road-map" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>With the remaining funds available from <a href="https://newsinitiative.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google News Initiative</a>, we plan to address the tight coupling between the front and back end and set up the OpenRefine Foundation for the next phases. The current implementation presents technical barriers for new contributors to engage with the community and limits the attractiveness of OpenRefine for developers. </p><p>Currently, all OpenRefine contributors are working on the project on top of their other academics, professional lives, and family commitments. While the Google funds help the core team to free some extra time to support OpenRefine, part-time involvement is not enough to address coming milestones (after all, we're a very small team!). We plan to hire fellow(s) / contractor(s) to work full time for a couple of months with the community and take the lead on the three following items (we will share more information regarding the fellow/contractor positions). </p><p>You can track the next phase in the Github project <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/projects/5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">separation of Front End and Back End</a>.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="prepare-front--back-end-separation">Prepare Front / Back-end separation<a class="hash-link" href="#prepare-front--back-end-separation" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Our goal is to have a full API exposing all OpenRefine operation and commands. This first phase focuses solely on documenting OpenRefine operations and commands available and designing the different API endpoints. The idea is to start small and grow the API over time by allowing for extensibility. In the process, we will take into account existing extensions developed for OpenRefine and support backward compatibility as much as we can.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="datagrid-enhancements">Datagrid Enhancements<a class="hash-link" href="#datagrid-enhancements" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>A faster grid technology with virtual DOM will set the foundation for faster scrolling, and interactive elements like drag and drop column moving and resizing, and column and row grouping to better support record mode (see the dedicated GitHub project for <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/projects/2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UI Improvements</a>. During the implementation, we can remove the custom bits of the frontend that are coupled directly to the back-end. The new datagrid implementation is tracked via <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/1347" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#1347</a>.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="data-storage-enhancements">Data Storage Enhancements<a class="hash-link" href="#data-storage-enhancements" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The group is looking at using Apache Arrow to improve the in-memory data model. An alternative, higher performance in-memory / on-disk data storage technology will help increase OpenRefine’s data processing capacity. The implementation of Apache Arrow is tracked in <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/1469" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#1469</a> and can be done independently from the API and datagrid implementation. </p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="following-phases">Following Phases<a class="hash-link" href="#following-phases" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Following the completion of the three previous phases, we want to: </p><ul><li>Implement the new API;</li><li>Leverage the new API and datagrid to move away from Jquery-based components and using React or Angular;</li><li>Ensure that we have extendable API points for our most important components;</li><li>Thanks to the decoupling of the front and back, we can answer the numerous requests from the community to support new data processing engines like Apache Spark or Google DataFlow / DataProc. Those items are tracked in the project <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/projects/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Performance Improvements</a>;</li><li>Keep supporting new features from requested from the community;</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: Spring 2016]]></title>
        <id>/2016/03/21/OpenRefine%20News%253A%20Spring%202016</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2016/03/21/OpenRefine%20News%253A%20Spring%202016"/>
        <updated>2016-03-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The OpenRefine community haven't been quiet during the Wintes months. Tons of new tutorials have been published in English, French, Italian, Spanish and Dutch and OpenRefine introduced to hundreds of new users at conferences, workshop and webinar. All the details below.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: December 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2016/01/08/OpenRefine News%3A December 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2016/01/08/OpenRefine News%3A December 2015"/>
        <updated>2016-01-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Happy new year Refiners! Now is time to look back and see what happen in the community through December. Open your agenda, we already have two  vents schedule for 2016]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy new year Refiners! Now is time to look back and see what happen in the community through December. Open your agenda, we already have two  vents schedule for 2016</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tutorials">Tutorials<a class="hash-link" href="#tutorials" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://twitter.com/psychemedia" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tony Hirst</a> share <a href="http://blog.ouseful.info/2015/12/18/ibm-datascientistworkbench-openrefine-rstudio-jupyter-notebooks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">his thoughts</a> on the new IBM Data Scientist WorkBench which combine in a single cloud platform OpenRefine, RStudio and Jupyter Notebooks.</p><p>Ever wanted to know how to use the template function to export your data in XML format? <a href="https://twitter.com/ndalyrose" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ndalyrose</a> explained how she <a href="https://t.co/ipHhvkuDom" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">used OpenRefine to create XML Records</a> from a spreadsheet for batch upload to Wikimedia. </p><p>The Louisiana Library Network (<a href="http://twitter.com/louislibraries" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@louislibraries</a>) published a slide deck on <a href="https://t.co/ahLOkL5NNP" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Data Wrangling with OpenRefine</a> including Presentation and Use case made.</p><p><a href="http://twitter.com/ppival" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ppival</a> put things in perspective and even if OpenRefine is an awesome tool for data cleaning he found that <a href="http://distlib.blogs.com/distlib/2015/12/open-refine-not-the-right-tool-for-this-job-twitter-archiving-and-geolocation.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">it may not be the right one</a> for twitter archiving and geolocation.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/MagdMartin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@MagdMartin</a> added a new knowledge base article to <a href="https://t.co/gPDWX6O9fa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check if value in one record are unique</a>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="development-update">Development Update<a class="hash-link" href="#development-update" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://twitter.com/AbsolutelyJeff" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@AbsolutelyJeff</a> released an update to his #VIAF reconciliation service. You can check it on his <a href="https://t.co/LVSaeTKfst" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Github repository</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="december-events-overview">December Events Overview<a class="hash-link" href="#december-events-overview" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">.<a href="https://twitter.com/ostephens" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ostephens</a> making things beautiful and searchable with <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@openrefine</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/citylis?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#citylis</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/librarycarpentry?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#librarycarpentry</a> <a href="https://t.co/YolXJFmwZJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/YolXJFmwZJ</a></p>— Ludi Price 柏詠璇 (@LudiPrice) <a href="https://twitter.com/LudiPrice/status/671394348072869888" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">November 30, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>The Week Four of the Library Carpentry program took place in London UK and <a href="https://github.com/LibraryCarpentry/week-four-library-carpentry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">focused on Open Refine</a> and was lead by <a href="https://twitter.com/ostephens" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ostephens</a>. </p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Now <a href="https://twitter.com/RubenVerborgh" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@RubenVerborgh</a> telling is about data cleaning, linking and enriching with OpenRefine <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/librarylab?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#librarylab</a> <a href="https://t.co/xHQTDVznpT" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/xHQTDVznpT</a></p>— GhentCDH (@GhentCDH) <a href="https://twitter.com/GhentCDH/status/672764217582338048" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">December 4, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>In Belgium, <a href="http://twitter.com/RubenVerborgh" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@RubenVerborgh</a> presented the Name Entity Extraction at the #LibraryLab.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">.<a href="https://twitter.com/Bahareh360" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Bahareh360</a> on cleaning data: Open Refine is amaaaazing <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/datadrivenjournalism?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#datadrivenjournalism</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nisdub?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#nisdub</a> <a href="https://t.co/y77kSawbJu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/y77kSawbJu</a></p>— Lisa Dupuy (@lisadupuy) <a href="https://twitter.com/lisadupuy/status/674238863045431296" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">December 8, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Finally at the News Impact Summit Dublin, <a href="http://twitter.com/Bahareh360" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Bahareh360</a> introduce OpenRefine to a crowd of journalist. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="coming-events">Coming Events<a class="hash-link" href="#coming-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Two workshop are schedule for 2016:</p><p>February 01, 2016 The University of Leicester organized a session on <a href="https://t.co/QSNzWIH3Zq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cleaning messy data with OpenRefine</a> for PhD Students and Staff </p><p>January 20, 2016 DVS Workshop: OpenRefine - Data Cleaning, Mining, Transformations, and Text Normalization at Duke University</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: November 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/12/04/OpenRefine News November 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/12/04/OpenRefine News November 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Once again welcome to the latest edition of our monthly update. Always exciting to update you on all the new developments that have been happening with OpenRefine, and the community as a whole.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once again welcome to the latest edition of our monthly update. Always exciting to update you on all the new developments that have been happening with OpenRefine, and the community as a whole.</p><p>This monthly update will showcase some good tutorials that were written by community members, popular events from November, and some events you can look forward to in December.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-tutorials-and-articles">New Tutorials and Articles<a class="hash-link" href="#new-tutorials-and-articles" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/louislibraries/data-wrangling-with-open-refine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Data Wrangling with OpenRefine</a> presentation and use case made at <a href="https://twitter.com/louislibraries" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@louislibraries</a>.</p><p>Use cases slide for the <a href="https://twitter.com/lobidOrg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@lobidOrg</a> made at the SWIB-15: <a href="http://hbz.github.io/slides/swib-15/#/28" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">API and reconciliation service</a> with OpenRefine by <a href="https://twitter.com/fsteeg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@fsteeg.</a></p><p>New Article regarding <a href="http://kb.refinepro.com/2015/11/split-multi-valued-cells-function-helps.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">limitations when splitting and joining multi-valued cells</a> in OpenRefine by <a href="https://twitter.com/MagdMartin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@MagdMartin.</a></p><p>We found this story really interesting and how <a href="https://twitter.com/KatieLaGrone" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@KatieLaGrone</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/WPTVTNIELS" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@WPTVTNIELS</a> used <a href="http://www.wptv.com/news/local-news/investigations/the-story-behind-the-story-dui-crashes-with-injuries-on-area-roads-and-intersections" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine to study DUI crashes.</a> </p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/importio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@importio</a> put  together an excellent list of <a href="http://blog.import.io/post/all-the-best-big-data-tools-and-how-to-use-them" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">all the best big data tools and how to use them</a>. Of course OpenRefine is one of them! </p><p>(In Chinese) <a href="http://zbryikt.github.io/openrefine-course/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine Course</a> by tkirby including regex, cluster, facet. Slides and Exercise</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="development-update">Development Update<a class="hash-link" href="#development-update" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We received two majors contributions last month.
First <a href="https://twitter.com/k_grons" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@k_grons</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/cora_jr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@cora_jr</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/roellephant" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@roellephant</a> built a new cluster export feature for OpenRefine. Their pull request is under review but you can test it right away <a href="https://github.com/amiaopensource/OpenRefine/releases/tag/2.6%2Bamia" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">from their repository</a>.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/pm5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@pm5</a> started a Node.js <a href="https://github.com/pm5/node-openrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">client library for controlling OpenRefine</a> similar to the existing one in ruby and python.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="november-events-recap">November Events Recap:<a class="hash-link" href="#november-events-recap" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>There was a rather interesting event organized by <a href="https://twitter.com/j_w_baker" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">James Baker</a> hashtag #libraraycarpentry, which was a program for introductory software skills. With better software comes better research, aimed at librarians, four sections three-hour introductory workshop held at the City University London Centre over a period of four weeks.</p><p>The numbers they got from the event are amazing to see, the event looks like it was very popular and well executed. The concept behind this workshop was to highlight the needs and requirements of library professionals that do not currently exist, detailed in James Bakers <a href="http://cradledincaricature.com/2015/12/01/library-carpentry-in-words-and-numbers-all-code-no-woodwork/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">final report of the event.</a> If you want greater details and more information i would strongly suggest having a look at the course content shared on <a href="https://github.com/LibraryCarpentry/week-four-library-carpentry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub.</a>  </p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/librarycarpentry?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#librarycarpentry</a> Okay, I think we've discovered conclusively that librarians who work with data LOVE OpenRefine.</p>— James Baker (@j_w_baker) <a href="https://twitter.com/j_w_baker/status/671401692886355968" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">November 30, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Another popular event that happened last month was the Semantic Web In Libraries Conference  <a href="http://swib.org/swib15/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">(SWIB15)</a> in Hamburg. The SWIB conference was aimed to provide substantial information on LOD developments relevant to the library world and to foster the exchange of ideas and experiences among practitioners. A large number of participants showed up from over 29 different countries really successful meet-up here. <a href="https://twitter.com/brinxmat" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rurik Greenall</a> posted a report on the event itself which is a solid read on his <a href="https://brinxmat.wordpress.com/2015/11/26/swib15/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">blog.</a></p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Spreadsheets, data tidying and open refine <a href="https://twitter.com/vlsci" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@vlsci</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/datacarpentry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@datacarpentry</a> morning session <a href="https://t.co/R0knY1t5rK" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/R0knY1t5rK</a></p>— Matthew Wakefield (@genomematt) <a href="https://twitter.com/genomematt/status/668585580553375744" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">November 23, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Students working with OpenRefine at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/biodatavis15?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#biodatavis15</a> recently held in Belgium. Very nice conference here that run a couple of days as well brought via <a href="https://twitter.com/jandot" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jan Aerts.</a></p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Students hard at work getting to grips with <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/openrefine?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#openrefine</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/biodatavis15?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#biodatavis15</a> <a href="https://t.co/dlwlWxNC0d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/dlwlWxNC0d</a></p>— Jan Aerts (@jandot) <a href="https://twitter.com/jandot/status/668778423674871809" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">November 23, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Last month RefinePro organized a new event as part of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Toronto-OpenRefine-Meetup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Toronto OpenRefine Meet-Up</a> series featuring use case from consultants and civic user. The summary of the <a href="http://refinepro.com/blog/toronto-openrefine-meet-up-review/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Meet-Up can be found here.</a>   </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="upcoming-events">Upcoming Events:<a class="hash-link" href="#upcoming-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>OpenRefine, <a href="http://www.univ-brest.fr/crbc/outils/Les_actualites/OpenRefine--Mes-donnees-a-la-machine.cid120624%20%E2%80%A6%20@OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mes données à la machine at the Université de Bretagne Occidentale,</a> UBO 08/12/2015</p><p><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/data-cleaning-using-open-refine-registration-19527673798" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Data Cleaning using OpenRefine in Melbourne, VIC 3010 Australia</a> December Monday 7th.</p><p>Cleaning &amp; exploring your data with OpenRefine Intersect Australia Tuesday, 8 December 2015 from 9:30 AM to 1:00 PM (AEDT) <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/uon-cleaning-exploring-your-data-with-open-refine-registration-19374206774?ref=ebapi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The University of Newcastle, NSW.</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: October 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/11/11/OpenRefine News October 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/11/11/OpenRefine News October 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-11-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this October edition of OpenRefine news: we have listed the latest tutorials and documentation published. Looking for events to attends in November? There is five OpenRefine events happening in the coming weeks.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this October edition of OpenRefine news: we have listed the latest tutorials and documentation published. Looking for events to attends in November? There is five OpenRefine events happening in the coming weeks. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tutorials-and-articles">Tutorials and Articles<a class="hash-link" href="#tutorials-and-articles" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Find out how to <a href="http://onlinejournalismblog.com/2015/10/21/how-to-convert-xml-or-json-into-spreadsheets-using-open-refine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">convert XML or JSON</a>  into spreadsheets using OpenRefine by <a href="https://twitter.com/paulbradshaw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@paulbradshaw</a></p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/SI_Stellies" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@SI_Stellies</a> shared <a href="http://code4sa.org/2015/10/09/OpenRefine-5-steps.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">five steps in OpenRefine that can save hours</a>. The publication is related to the war on poverty program in South Africa and how your data set can easily be misinterpreted. </p><p><a href="http://abdelrahmanhosny.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abdelrahman Hosny</a> wrote a breakdown and analysis as well and show how to <a href="http://abdelrahmanhosny.com/2015/10/07/cleaning-messy-data-using-open-refine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">clean messy data using OpenRefine,</a>.</p><p>Brief tutorial from <a href="https://twitter.com/church_c" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@church</a> on <a href="http://www.christophermchurch.com/adding-unique-identifiers-in-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">adding unique identifiers</a> with leading zeroes in OpenRefine. Sometimes you may want to add unique identifiers (UIDs) to your data in OpenRefine (eg. migrating the data into a Database Management System (DBMS) like Access or Filemaker). This is a basic guideline of how to go about doing that step by step. </p><p>Good video here shows how Using OpenRefine to process data from the Past Perfect records using the <a href="https://vimeo.com/139751008" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MADE authority.</a>  </p><p>Publication on how to <a href="http://epublications.marquette.edu/lib_fac/81/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Identifying potential headings for Authority</a> work using III Sierra, MS Excel and OpenRefine by <a href="https://twitter.com/LibWorkflowEx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@LibWorkflowEx</a> </p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/thadguidry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thad Guidry</a> bloged on how to display <a href="http://savetheworldnotyourmoney.blogspot.ca/2015/10/display-html-content-from-url-within.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HTML content from a URL within OpenRefine,</a>. It works great if you’re doing small reconciling task.</p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/hpiedcoq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@hpiedcoq</a> gives us a brief outline on <a href="http://oh-w.tf/post/131481133375/openrefine-filter-data-by-period-of-time" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">how to filter data</a>, by time period, so it’s easier to work with.</p><p>Lots of tutorials and articles on regex, OpenRefine, Google Fusion Tables &amp; more from <a href="http://www.intersect.org.au/course-resources" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Intersect Australia.</a> Shared via <a href="https://twitter.com/a_e_lang" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@a_e_lang</a></p><h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="in-french">In French<a class="hash-link" href="#in-french" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h5><p> <a href="https://cquest.hackpad.com/OpenRefine-et-gocodage-avec-adresse.data.gouv.fr-PCbRafrVuef" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine et géocodage avec </a> by <a href="https://cquest.hackpad.com/ep/profile/qnmPcumtxjo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Christian Quest</a>.</p><h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="in-chinese">In Chinese<a class="hash-link" href="#in-chinese" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h5><p><a href="http://www.cnblogs.com/1zhk/p/4790100.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine导入CSV文件，数据清理后导出JSON格式</a> published by <a href="http://www.cnblogs.com/1zhk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HK Zhang.</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="october-events">October Events<a class="hash-link" href="#october-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Among the several workshop on OpenRefine that happened through October, <a href="https://twitter.com/bobbledavidson" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rob Davidson</a> presented at #COMBINE15. </p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Rapt audience in <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/COMBINE15?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#COMBINE15</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/datacarpentry" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@datacarpentry</a> wkshop. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenRefine?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#OpenRefine</a> is popular! <a href="http://t.co/umHAwD4KzP" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/umHAwD4KzP</a></p>— Rob Davidson (@bobbledavidson) <a href="https://twitter.com/bobbledavidson/status/651556849636913152" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">October 7, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>At #odcamp Day 2, among session on health care and dataviz, one on using OpenRefine to generate RDF. Thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/marc_in_london" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marc Barto.</a> for sharing</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">On the programme for <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/odcamp?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#odcamp</a> Day 2: <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenSensorsIO" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenSensorsIO</a> , Health Care,  Open Refine, data viz, Lidar &amp; 3D and more <a href="http://t.co/14IRO0LiGB" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/14IRO0LiGB</a></p>— Marc Barto (@marc_in_london) <a href="https://twitter.com/marc_in_london/status/653154972880777216" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">October 11, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="events">Events<a class="hash-link" href="#events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Toronto OpenRefine is having a Meet-Up this up and coming month, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Toronto-OpenRefine-Meetup/events/226377148/?a=ra1_te" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nov 17th   How OpenRefine can help your next data projects?</a> With user showcase make sure you don’t miss out on this and sign up, guest speakers <a href="http://twitter.com/biancawylie" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bianca Wylie</a> and <a href="http://www.itcentralstation.com/users/heerbod-etemadi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Heerbod Etemadi</a> already confirmed.</p><p>Hands-on intro to data cleaning with OpenRefine workshop <a href="https://twitter.com/stanfordlibs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stanford Libraries</a> Workshop is on <a href="http://library.stanford.edu/research/data-management-services/events#refine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tuesday Nov. 17, 2015.</a></p><p>Camperdown <a href="https://twitter.com/sydney_uni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">University of Sydney</a>: Cleaning &amp; exploring your data with Open Refine on <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/usyd-cleaning-exploring-your-data-with-open-refine-registration-19037151633?ref=ebapi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thursday 19th November.</a>  </p><p>Metadata tools, working with MarcEdit and OpenRefine Workshop <a href="https://catandindexgroup.wordpress.com/2015/10/27/metadata-tools-working-with-marcedit-and-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Friday 20th Nov in Birmingham.</a>  </p><p>How to automate the administration of PPC campaigns using OpenRefine <a href="http://www.marketingfestival.cz/en/workshop/karel-rujzl" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thursday November 26th Brno, Czech Republic.</a></p><p>OpenRefine Workshop in Gent (Belgium) <a href="http://ow.ly/TTpg3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Friday 4th Dec.</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: September 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/10/13/OpenRefine News September 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/10/13/OpenRefine News September 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-10-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are thrilled to share with you some updates from our end, new and exciting developments that have been happening with the community in September, the buzz around the new online OpenRefine Foundation course.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are thrilled to share with you some updates from our end, new and exciting developments that have been happening with the community in September, the buzz around the new online <a href="http://bigdatauniversity.com/bdu-wp/bdu-course/introduction-to-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine Foundation</a> course.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-course-and-article">New Course and Article<a class="hash-link" href="#new-course-and-article" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://bigdatauniversity.com/bdu-wp/bdu-course/introduction-to-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RefinePro</a> launched the new Online OpenRefine Foundation Course, to assist in the learning of basic data science by providing structure and direction to the students. This course lets you learn the basics of OpenRefine and data manipulation in only 7 hours. There are a total of 23 instructional videos and 7 hands-on labs split into 5 challenging lessons.</p><p><a href="http://blog.kwantu.net/author/rob-worthington" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rob Worthington</a> wrote an interesting and content filled article this month, on <a href="http://blog.kwantu.net/how-to-clean-up-messy-data-using-open-refine?utm_campaign=KM&amp;utm_content=20726810&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">how to clean up messy data</a> using OpenRefine. Great step by step tutorial to find, remove duplicates, group similar data and lots more for new users.</p><p>In his latest tutorial, <a href="http://blog.ouseful.info/author/psychemedia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tony Hirst</a> shows how to <a href="http://blog.ouseful.info/2015/09/04/converting-spreadsheet-rows-to-text-based-summary-reports-using-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">convert Spreadsheet Rows to Text Based Summary Reports Using OpenRefine</a></p><p>#####In German<br>
<!-- -->Good article about @OpenRefine and the <a href="http://www.tanner.de/blog/datenanalyse-und-optimierung-mit-openrefine-3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">handling of large amounts of data</a> released, by <a href="http://www.tanner.de/blog/author/alexanderwitzigmann/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alexander Witzigmann</a>.</p><h5 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="in-mandarin">In Mandarin<a class="hash-link" href="#in-mandarin" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h5><p>Really interesting to see how the community had come a long way and now the reach is on a global scale.  Check <a href="https://twitter.com/tzangms" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@tzangms</a> using <a href="http://blog.infographics.tw/2015/09/openrefine-introduction/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine to show how you can use facets and filters.</a></p><p>##Development Update</p><p>Andrey at <a href="https://twitter.com/Fusepool" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Fusepool</a>  release of a new OpenRefine binary with an RDF extension, get it here: <a href="https://t.co/Q6RV8q4LWl" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/fusepoolP3/OpenRefine/releases/tag/2.6-beta.2-rdf</a></p><p>The OpenRefine core development team finished to close the issue related to the 2.6 release and prepare a new Release Candidate in the coming weeks. Keep an eye on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/openrefine-dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developer mailing list</a> for any announcement. </p><p>A big thanks to <a href="https://github.com/nestorjal" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">nestorjal rudygt</a>  and <a href="https://github.com/nachomezzadra" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">nachomezzadra</a> for helping with the Spanish translation of OpenRefine. It will be part of the 2.6 release. </p><p>Thank you also to <a href="https://github.com/mgalushka" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">mgalushka</a> and  <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aopen+author%3Ajackyq2015" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">jackyq2015</a> for their merged pull request through September.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="september-event">September Event<a class="hash-link" href="#september-event" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="data-science-training-4-librarians-dst4l">Data Science Training 4 Librarians (DST4L)<a class="hash-link" href="#data-science-training-4-librarians-dst4l" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>In September the Data Science Training 4 Librarians (DST4L) initially organized by Harvard Library moved to Copenhagen at the Technical University of Denmark for a three days sessions. The workshop started with a full day on OpenRefine with Simon Hengchen (<a href="https://twitter.com/_shengche" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@_shengche</a>), Raphael Hubain (<a href="https://twitter.com/rhubain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">(@rHubain)</a>) and Martin Magdinier (<!-- -->[@Martin Magdinier]<!-- -->(<a href="https://twitter.com/Martin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://twitter.com/Martin</a> Magdinier)) with support via twitter by the rest of the community.      </p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/MagdMartin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@MagdMartin</a> leading the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Dst4l?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#Dst4l</a> crowd into refined aspects of <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/GREL?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#GREL</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/MyDTU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@MyDTU</a> <a href="http://t.co/ApXuJ5oTRb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/ApXuJ5oTRb</a></p>— Michael Svendsen (@tullemich) <a href="https://twitter.com/tullemich/status/641564358976380928" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">September 9, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p>Great support and help all around, lots on hands on deck. Whenever people required assistance, the community rallied and provided solutions.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/sfk01" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@sfk01</a> Good news! The <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a> parseHTML() function parses HTML, XHTML, and XML. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dst4l?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#dst4l</a> /cc <a href="https://twitter.com/libcce" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@libcce</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/karstenkryger" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@karstenkryger</a> (dupe - forgot <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dst4l?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#dst4l</a>)</p>— Tom Morris (@tfmorris) <a href="https://twitter.com/tfmorris/status/641659157473574912" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">September 9, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><p><a href="https://twitter.com/PittLibraries" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PittLibraries</a> The University of Pittsburgh had a good workshop on how to refine data using @OpenRefine.</p><p>Sharing knowledge on @OpenRefine workshop happening in Argentina. Really good to see that no matter where you are, you have someone knowledgable of OpenRefine to the community.     </p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="es" dir="ltr">Qué miran? Cómo "masajear" datos con <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a> en el taller <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/CartografiaDeDatos?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#CartografiaDeDatos</a> de <a href="https://twitter.com/FLACSOVirtualAR" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@FLACSOVirtualAR</a>. <a href="http://t.co/Jb3BDXYwYZ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/Jb3BDXYwYZ</a></p>— Sergio Sorin (@pollatos) <a href="https://twitter.com/pollatos/status/643886036955828224" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">September 15, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="up-coming-workshop-and-events">Up Coming Workshop and Events<a class="hash-link" href="#up-coming-workshop-and-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://lodlam.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Linked Open Data in Libraries Archives and Museums (LODLAM)</a> services as a borderless network of enthusiasts, technicians, professionals and any number of other people who are interested in or working with Linked Open Data pertaining to galleries, libraries, archives, and museums. Currently looking for workshop leaders that can run various conferences throughout 2015-16 teaching <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Az8ylu76m-bcSDhgYVf-31s2-OLOkHmvSx5k_I9a-no/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LODLAM</a>, if you have time and the knowledge this would help a lot of people.  </p><p><a href="http://cposc.org/sessions/introduction-to-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Introduction to OpenRefine at Central PA Open Source Conference</a> 2015-10-17 by Heather Myers. Data is always a hot topic, this conference is to educate and talk about cleaning this data. Increased demand for this product leads to more and more workshops, which is really good to see. </p><p><a href="http://calendar.duke.edu/events/show?fq=id%3ACAL-8a0870ef-4f40a47f-014f-43b8961b-00006e91demobedework%40mysite.edu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DVS Workshop: OpenRefine: Data Mining and Transformations, Text Normalization</a>  Oct 20, 2015 at Duke University.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: August 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/09/04/OpenRefine News August 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/09/04/OpenRefine News August 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-09-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Did you took a break from OpenRefine in August, fear of missing something? No worries, the August update got you covered.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you took a break from OpenRefine in August, fear of missing something? No worries, the August update got you covered.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-tutorials-and-articles">New Tutorials and Articles<a class="hash-link" href="#new-tutorials-and-articles" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Most of August tutorials and new publication revolve around using OpenRefine with third party service, either by call an API or fetching web pages. </p><p>Catch up <a href="https://twitter.com/silkdotco" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Silk</a> tutorial and video webinar on how to <a href="http://blog.silk.co/post/127234807482/from-ombd-to-gender-data-on-film-directors-how-to" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">clean and enhance data using APIs, OpenRefine, and Regex</a></p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/hpiedcoq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@hpiedcoq</a> have been sharing a list of JSON recipes and how to on github:</p><ul><li><a href="http://t.co/LLgNKCjLa5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How-to retrieve infos on french companies</a></li><li><a href="https://t.co/esuw1Xz7kk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to check validity of E.U. VAT numbers using OpenRefine and the VIES platform?</a></li><li><a href="https://github.com/hpiedcoq/Mass-IP-identifier-for-OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mass IP identifier for OpenRefine</a></li></ul><p>On a similart topic, <a href="https://github.com/paldhous" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">paldhous</a> shared his <a href="https://github.com/paldhous/refine-geocoder" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">recipe to geocode list of addresses in Open Refine, using Bing and MapQuest Open APIs</a></p><p>New reconcilitation service for The <a href="http://beta.lobid.org/organisations" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">lobid-organisations service</a>. They provides a web API to a comprehensive dataset of library institutions in Germany. All the details to connect to their reconciliation service is <a href="https://github.com/hbz/lobid-organisations/issues/55" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">on their github</a></p><p>In Korean Neuro Associates share a complete <a href="http://t.co/y9aa1obLiO" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">slideshow introducing OpenRefine main functionality</a>.</p><p>In French, <a href="http://t.co/fmnKzscOyo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">clusteriser vos urls avec OpenRefine</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="development-update">Development Update<a class="hash-link" href="#development-update" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>As we keep closing the latest issue for the 2.6 release, <a href="http://twitter.com/cm_harlow" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@cm_harlow</a> shared her <a href="http://t.co/ssXxYPbqfd" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">speaker's notes for #c4lmdc OpenRefine Recon Service workshop</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="august-events-summary">August Events Summary<a class="hash-link" href="#august-events-summary" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>MSU’s Institute for Digital Archaeology Method &amp; Practice, took place August 18 and 19 and included a session on OpenRefine led by <a href="https://twitter.com/DEJPett" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@DEJPett</a>. You can catch up with the <a href="https://t.co/tn5q0NdrXx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">workshop task</a> and <a href="https://t.co/BOgqC5Qw4N" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tutorial shared on texas diplomatic correspondence</a>. </p><div align="center"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Omgosh....OpenRefine has the potential so make so many basic data management tasks SOOOO much easier. Very excited. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/msudai?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#msudai</a></p>— Mary E. Lennon (@MaryELennon) <a href="https://twitter.com/MaryELennon/status/633789661840863233" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">August 18, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div><p>Meanwhile in Argentina, the HackHacker Media party was a great success. Thank you to <a href="https://twitter.com/jjelosua" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@jjelosua</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/rusosnith" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@rusosnith</a> for sharing your OpenRefine knowledge! </p><div align="center"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Workshop de scrapeo de datos con Openrefine de <a href="https://twitter.com/rusosnith" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@rusosnith</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hhba?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#hhba</a> <a href="http://t.co/Hs3Wp8YAQ2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/Hs3Wp8YAQ2</a></p>— Hacks Hackers Bs As (@HacksHackersBA) <a href="https://twitter.com/HacksHackersBA/status/636973877432852481" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">August 27, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div><div align="center"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="es" dir="ltr">Workshop de <a href="https://twitter.com/jjelosua" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@jjelosua</a> en la <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/mediaparty2015?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#mediaparty2015</a> de <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hhba?src=hash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#hhba</a> Expresiones regulares y OpenRefine <a href="https://twitter.com/HacksHackersBA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@hackshackersBA</a></p>— C.Fernández Moores (@carolafmoores) <a href="https://twitter.com/carolafmoores/status/637372584431124484" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">August 28, 2015</a></blockquote><script async="" src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="coming-workshop-and-events">Coming Workshop and Events<a class="hash-link" href="#coming-workshop-and-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://lodlam.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LODLAM</a> is looking for folks to teach #OpenRefine #SPARQL and other tools throughout 2015-16. <a href="http://t.co/q9XUj6LUAx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sign up here</a></p><p>Come at one of the coming OpenRefine events to sharpe your data cleaning skills:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/cleaning-and-exploring-your-data-with-open-refine-division-of-natural-sciences-usyd-registration-18238734546?ref=twitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn to use Open Refine to clean up messy data</a>. Free course for <a href="https://twitter.com/Sydney_Uni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Sydney_Uni</a> researchers Tue September 8</li><li><a href="http://ow.ly/NOxgm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Data Scientist Training for Librarians (DST4L)</a> comes to Copenhagen with an all day OpenRefine session Sep 9</li><li><a href="http://cposc.org/sessions/introduction-to-openrefine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Introduction to OpenRefine</a> at Central PA Open Source Conference 2015-10-17 by <a href="https://twitter.com/cposc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@cposc</a></li><li><a href="http://calendar.duke.edu/events/show?fq=id%3ACAL-8a0870ef-4f40a47f-014f-43b8961b-00006e91demobedework%40mysite.edu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DVS Workshop: OpenRefine: Data Mining and Transformations, Text Normalization</a> Oct 20, 2015 at Duke University</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: July 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/08/07/OpenRefine News July 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/08/07/OpenRefine News July 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-08-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is time to look back at developments who happened in the community through July. Plenty of new tutorials in English, French, German and Czech, and an update on progress on the 2.6 release.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is time to look back at developments who happened in the community through July. Plenty of new tutorials in English, French, German and Czech, and an update on progress on the 2.6 release.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-tutorials-and-articles">New Tutorials and Articles<a class="hash-link" href="#new-tutorials-and-articles" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="english">English<a class="hash-link" href="#english" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><a href="https://twitter.com/owenstephen" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OwenStephen</a> wrote a series of 5 articles on working with MARC with text editors, MarcEdit and OpenRefine. a must read for every librarian: <a href="http://www.meanboyfriend.com/overdue_ideas/tag/fixmarc/?orderby=date&amp;order=ASC" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A worked example fixing marc data</a></p><p><a href="http://twitter.com/cm_harlow" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@cm_harlow</a> have been working on a local python based reconciliation service for <a href="http://www.geonames.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">geonames</a> to add Geonames information based on geographic subject names. Check the <a href="https://github.com/cmh2166/geonames-reconcile" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">repository</a> and <a href="http://christinaharlow.com/walkthrough-of-geonames-recon-service" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">read her step by step walkthrough</a> to run the service.</p><p>A new <a href="http://ow.ly/P5jR1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video tutorial</a> has been published, describing the steps to generate a RDF with OpenRefine and the RDF extension.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="french">French<a class="hash-link" href="#french" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><a href="http://punktokomo.abes.fr/2015/07/10/911/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine ou comment passer des listes aux applications ABES : illustration avec IdRef et theses.fr</a></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="german">German<a class="hash-link" href="#german" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Datenanalyse und -optimierung mit OpenRefine
<a href="http://www.tanner.de/blog/datenanalyse-und-optimierung-mit-openrefine-1/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a> and <a href="http://www.tanner.de/blog/datenanalyse-und-optimierung-mit-openrefine-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a> - By <a href="http://twitter.com/TANNER_AG" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@TANNER_AG</a></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="czech">Czech<a class="hash-link" href="#czech" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><a href="http://blog.medio.cz/open-refine-snadna-cesta-k-ziskani-klicovych-dat-z-naseptavace" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">snadná cesta k získání klíčových dat z našeptávače</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="development-update">Development Update<a class="hash-link" href="#development-update" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Through July we received five pull request including four toward the 2.6 release. Those are currently under review and should be merged shortly.  </p><p><a href="https://github.com/jackyq2015" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Qi Cui</a> can now apply milestones and labels on the OpenRefine issue. Over 20 new issues have been opened last month and an extra person to help with the triage is more than welcome. Thank you to everyone who took the time to open issue and report bugs. </p><p>The wikidata team start setting up a <a href="https://tools.wmflabs.org/wikidata-reconcile/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">reconciliation service for OpenRefine</a>. This is a work under progress and the API implementation is incomplete. Things may change or stop working at any time. You can join the discussion on the <a href="https://lists.wikimedia.org/pipermail/wikidata/2015-July/006776.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wikimedia discussion list</a></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="workshop-and-events">Workshop and Events<a class="hash-link" href="#workshop-and-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="last-month-events">Last month events:<a class="hash-link" href="#last-month-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Thanks to all the presenter and OpenRefine advocate who have done presentation at #DHOxSS #OSAD15 #HILT2015 #DatacampUY #SBCWest2015 #c4ln2015</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="upcoming-events">Upcoming events:<a class="hash-link" href="#upcoming-events" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><ul><li>Upcoming METRO Workshop <a href="http://twitter.com/mnylc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@mnylc</a> - Clean Collections: <a href="http://metro.org/events/659/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Using OpenRefine to Manage Messy Metadata</a>
(sold out) </li><li><a href="http://ow.ly/NOxgm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Data Scientist Training for Librarians (DST4L)</a> comes to Copenhagen with an all day OpenRefine session Sep 9: </li><li>UMBHLCuration will be doing a workshop on structured data wrangling w/Python and OpenRefine for the midmichdp at Albion College on October 8th.</li></ul><p>Do you want to annouce your next event / OpenRefine session, let us know via twitter: <a href="http://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine News: June 2015]]></title>
        <id>/2015/07/01/OpenRefine News June 2015</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/07/01/OpenRefine News June 2015"/>
        <updated>2015-07-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Currently most of the communication around OpenRefine done is through the mailing list and our twitter account where information are quickly buried for someone not following the project on day to day basis. Those monthly summary highlights key events and contributions in the community and hopefully help to better circulate key information.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Currently most of the communication around OpenRefine done is through the mailing list and our twitter account where information are quickly buried for someone not following the project on day to day basis. Those monthly summary highlights key events and contributions in the community and hopefully help to better circulate key information. </p><p>Feedback on the format and content are welcome. Ping us on twitter <a href="http://twitter.com/OpenRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a> if we are missing information.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-tutorials-and-articles">New Tutorials and Articles<a class="hash-link" href="#new-tutorials-and-articles" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>If you are new to OpenRefine, Alvin Chang published an excellent <a href="http://trendct.org/2015/04/24/john-jonathan-and-johnny-how-to-merge-them-in-open-refine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">introduction to clustering</a> maybe OpenRefine most appreciated feature with new users. For more advanced users, <a href="http://twitter.com/UMBHLCuration" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@UMBHLCuration</a> published a tutorial on <a href="http://archival-integration.blogspot.ca/2015/06/normalizing-dates-with-openrefine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Normalizing Dates with OpenRefine</a>.</p><p>At the Toronto OpenRefine UnConference, I presented on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/MartinMagdinier/iterative-data-discovery-and-transformation-with-open-refine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Iterative data discovery and transformation with OpenRefine</a> explaining why OpenRefine is an essential tool for non technical subject matter expert when working with data. To dig further on the topic with the article <a href="http://ow.ly/OMC6X" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Agile Data Process with OpenRefine.</a> </p><p>If you are working in a library. Checkout the records of this month NCompass Live: <a href="http://nlc.nebraska.gov/scripts/calendar/eventshow.asp?ProgID=14290" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Metadata Manipulations: Using MarcEdit and OpenRefine</a>. <a href="http://twitter.com/silviaegt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@silviaegt</a> also published his slides of hisDHBenelux talk with links to <a href="https://prezi.com/atejujdtq8g9/literary-constellations/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIAF reconc. for OpenRefine &amp; cartoDB</a>.</p><p>Finally a great use case presented by <a href="http://twitter.com/hpiedcoq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@hpiedcoq</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/jvilledieu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@jvilledieu</a>: <a href="http://ow.ly/OkxZG" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to visualize your Facebook network</a> with OpenRefine outwit and Neo4j.</p><p>We also have a new resource published in French and Italian:</p><ul><li><a href="http://t.co/npSEf6TJH8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Créer un référentiel pour le #LOD avec #OpenRefine et #Gingo</a> by <a href="http://twitter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Invisu</a> </li><li><a href="http://ow.ly/NOxBi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tutorial per come farsi del geocoding in casa partendo da un elenco di indirizzi</a></li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="development-update">Development Update<a class="hash-link" href="#development-update" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="openrefine26-rc1">OpenRefine2.6 RC1<a class="hash-link" href="#openrefine26-rc1" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Over the last three months we received update to translate OpenRefine interface in Spanish and French. The  This will complete the current English, Italian and Chineese version. </p><p>We are currently testing the <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/releases/tag/v2.6-rc1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2.6 RC1 version</a> as a quick checkpoint to allow us to verify all the fixes that have been made since beta 1 and figure out what remaining loose ends need to be cleaned up. More information on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/openrefine-dev/eip_ikUiNvA/voPoHqkuS0EJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developer mailing list</a></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reconciliation-and-matching-framework-rmf">Reconciliation and Matching Framework (RMF)<a class="hash-link" href="#reconciliation-and-matching-framework-rmf" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p><a href="https://github.com/MattBlissett" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Matthew Blissett</a> with the support of the <a href="http://www.kew.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Royal Botanic Gardens</a> in London are releasing <a href="https://github.com/RBGKew/Reconciliation-and-Matching-Framework" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reconciliation and Matching Framework (RMF)</a>, a framework to allow the matching of string entities using customised sets of transformations and matchers, plus a tool to produce the necessary configurations and another to expose them as OpenRefine reconciliation services. </p><p>###GOKB annoucement:</p><p>GOKb, the Global Open Knowledgebase, is a community-managed project that aims to describe electronic journals and books, publisher packages, and platforms which host the resources. GOKb use OpenRefine (with a specially designed extension) as our major mechanism of getting data into GOKb - exploiting the ability to clean up the data (which tends to come from publishers and can be of variable quality) and to re-apply changes to future data from the same publisher/supplier.</p><p>GOKb opened to ‘public preview’ in January 2015, and you can signup for an account and access the service at <a href="https://gokb.kuali.org/gokb/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://gokb.kuali.org/gokb/</a></p><p>Several hundred ejournal packages, and associated information about the ejournal titles, platforms and organisations have been added to the knowledgebase over the past few months. OpenRefine is used to do much of the work to get data ready for loading into GOKb.</p><p>Alongside this work of adding content GOKb have also opened up APIs to interact with the service, which could be useful to others using OpenRefine to work with data relating to journals. In particular the ‘Coreference service’ allows you to look up identifiers (such as ISSNs) and get back journal title information and other IDs associated with that title (as JSON or XML).</p><p>They are interested in:</p><ul><li>Talking to people who use OpenRefine and would like to make use of such a service</li><li>If there is some interest, what support/documentation people would like to see</li><li>Understanding if we can offer different/better services based on the GOKb data for OpenRefine (e.g. would different data GOKb has be of interest? Would a reconciliation service for journal titles? etc.)</li></ul><p>More details and join the discussion on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/openrefine/c_BM4H9jk2o/x4ED1VB_WwUJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">user mailing list</a></p><p>##Workshop and Events</p><p>OpenRefine Twitter feed have been busy last months with over 12 presentations of OpenRefine made! Thank you to our evangelists who introduce OpenRefine to librians, journalist, goverement and open date professional among other groups. Top hastag are: </p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-T8LGwAEz3YQ/VZQvLSKD9NI/AAAAAAAANKE/j8k6PoN6YZM/s1600/news-june2015.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-T8LGwAEz3YQ/VZQvLSKD9NI/AAAAAAAANKE/j8k6PoN6YZM/s1600/news-june2015.png" class="inset"></a><p>Want to connect with fellow Refiners? The following events have been announced so far. Ping us on twitter <a href="http://twitter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@OpenRefine</a> to announce your event:</p><ul><li><a href="http://tinyurl.com/nsjrhmm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Several Cleaning &amp; Exploring data w OpenRefine workshop</a> available through July with #DH2015 in Australia. </li><li><a href="http://ow.ly/NOxgm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Data Scientist Training for Librarians (DST4L)</a> comes to Copenhagen with an all day OpenRefine session Sep 9: </li><li>UMBHLCuration will be doing a workshop on structured data wrangling w/Python and OpenRefine for the midmichdp at Albion College on October 8th.</li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mapping OpenRefine Ecosystem]]></title>
        <id>/2015/01/26/Mapping-OpenRefine-ecosystem</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2015/01/26/Mapping-OpenRefine-ecosystem"/>
        <updated>2015-01-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since the OpenRefine move to Github two years ago, the project has reached a mature stage, and only maintenance work has been done with the release of openrefine2.6-beta. At the same time, the project kept gaining traction with over a thousand weekly downloads and usage with various audiences in particular fields of application. One out of four OpenRefine users identify themselves as librarians, with Researchers and Open Data enthusiasts representing the second largest user group, and Data Journalists and Semantic Web Professionals completing the picture (see the full 2014 survey results)]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since the OpenRefine move to Github two years ago, the project has reached a mature stage, and only maintenance work has been done with the release of openrefine2.6-beta. At the same time, the project kept gaining traction with over a thousand weekly downloads and usage with various audiences in particular fields of application. One out of four OpenRefine users identify themselves as librarians, with Researchers and Open Data enthusiasts representing the second largest user group, and Data Journalists and Semantic Web Professionals completing the picture (see the full <a href="http://openrefine.org/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2014 survey results</a>)</p><p>OpenRefine offers an innovative workflow from data ingestion to consumption, with a capacity to reconcile information consistency and work with remote data processing services. It integrates with over 16 reconciliation services and has 8 community contributed plugins that extend its capability. You can interact directly with the API of 4 other platforms within the context of tasks in OpenRefine alchemyAPI, Zemanta, dataTXT and Crowdflower. The following map lists the different services and plugins working with OpenRefine, as well as projects that have done heavy customization to add OpenRefine in their data manipulation processes.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="map-of-openrefine-ecosystem">Map of OpenRefine Ecosystem<a class="hash-link" href="#map-of-openrefine-ecosystem" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2015-01-23-Mapping-OpenRefine-Ecosystem/openrefine-map.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2015-01-23-Mapping-OpenRefine-Ecosystem/openrefine-map.png" class="inset"></a><p>The full list of the reconciliation services is up to date on <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconcilable-Data-Sources" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenRefine wiki</a>, link to each the extension are available on the <a href="http://openrefine.org/download.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">download page</a>. Integration and extensions can be broken down by user community types:</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="general-usage">General Usage<a class="hash-link" href="#general-usage" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><a href="http://openrefine.org/download.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Several extensions</a> are available to add new functionality to OpenRefine:</p><ul><li>Diff </li><li>Stats calculate</li><li>BITS VIB</li><li>NER extension</li><li>extraCTU and geoXtension</li></ul><p><a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconcilable-Data-Sources#general" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Custom reconciliation services</a> can be build using the following project developed by the <a href="https://okfn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenKnowledge Foundation</a>:</p><ul><li>Reconcile-csv, </li><li>nomenklatura </li><li>SPARQL endpoints. </li></ul><p><a href="http://refinepro.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RefinePro</a> offer hosted services (cloud and on-premise) of OpenRefine providing extra compute power, access from multiple devices and multi user management.</p><p>Finally a <a href="https://github.com/maxogden/refine-python" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">python</a> and <a href="https://github.com/maxogden/refine-ruby" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ruby</a> library enable batch processing of the history of an OpenRefine project.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="librarians">Librarians<a class="hash-link" href="#librarians" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Directly from OpenRefine, <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconcilable-Data-Sources#librarians" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">six different reconciliation services</a> are available to librarians:</p><ul><li>Vivo</li><li>FundRef</li><li>JournalTOCs</li><li>VIAF</li><li>FAST (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Reconciliation</li><li>Library of Congress Subject Headings</li></ul><p>Librarians with a <a href="https://gokb.kuali.org/gokb/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Global Open Knowledge base (GOKB)</a> account can export and import data directly to this repository of electronic journals and books, publisher packages. The <a href="https://github.com/k-int/gokb-phase1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GOKB extension</a> tightly integrate OpenRefine with GOKB workflow.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="open-data">Open Data<a class="hash-link" href="#open-data" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In Open Data, users of CKAN, the Open Source data portal software edited by the Open Knowledge Foundation, can prepare (normalize, cleanup, etc.) their data before publishing them via <a href="https://github.com/opendatatrentino/OpenDataRise" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenDataRise</a>, a distribution of OpenRefine. <a href="https://github.com/opendatatrentino/OpenDataRise" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenDataRise</a>, allows also insertion/update of entities to a target knowledge base, for now the only reconciliation service supported is Entitypedia (which is yet to go public). Other services might get eventually supported. </p><p>Directly from OpenRefine, several <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconcilable-Data-Sources#open-data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">reconciliation services</a> are available to the open data community:</p><ul><li>Influencer Explorer from the Sunlight foundation</li><li>dbpedia</li><li>OpenCorporate</li><li>Ordnance Survey</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="biodiversity-researchers">Biodiversity Researchers<a class="hash-link" href="#biodiversity-researchers" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Biodiversity researchers benefit from direct access to <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Reconcilable-Data-Sources#biodiversity-researchers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">seven reconciliation services</a> including:</p><ul><li>EOL</li><li>NCBI taxonomy</li><li>Ubio FindIT</li><li>WORMS</li><li>GBIF</li><li>Global Names Index</li><li>IPNI</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="semantic-web">Semantic Web<a class="hash-link" href="#semantic-web" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Semantic Web Professionals have access to the RDF and Link Media Framewok (LMF) <a href="http://openrefine.org/download.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">extensions</a> to produce and consume linked data. The <a href="https://github.com/sparkica/LODRefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LODRefine distribution</a> integrated extensions that make transition from tabular data to Linked Data a bit easier. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="under-development-projects">Under Development Projects<a class="hash-link" href="#under-development-projects" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p><strong>SparkRefine</strong> - right now it's just a prototype developed by Andrey Bratus, bachelor's student at the university of Trento in Italy with Spaziodati in the context of the <a href="http://p3.fusepool.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fusepool P3 project</a>. The initial results are avaialbe in <a href="http://d3s.disi.unitn.it/~mega/andrey_thesis.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Andrey’s thesis</a>, but the <a href="https://github.com/andreybratus/RefineOnSpark" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">codebase</a> is not in particularly good shape.</p><p><strong><a href="https://github.com/fusepoolP3/p3-batchrefine" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BatchRefine</a></strong> is a collection of wrappers for running OpenRefine in batch mode developed by Spaziodati for Fusepool P3.</p><p><strong><a href="http://dev.redlink.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Redfine</a></strong> is Redlink internal bundle of OpenRefine. The project is currently in development as they integrate some internal services into Redlink public API.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="deprecated">Deprecated<a class="hash-link" href="#deprecated" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The freebase extension is <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/issues/805" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">partly broken</a> and freebase announce the <a href="https://plus.google.com/109936836907132434202/posts/bu3z2wVqcQc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sunset of their services in 2015</a>.  The crowdflower extension should update to the new version of crowdflower’s API.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 survey results]]></title>
        <id>/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2014/08/29/2014-survey-results"/>
        <updated>2014-08-29T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Following the 2012 survey which gather 99 answers, I wanted to have a fresh picture on who are OpenRefine users. The 2014 survey received 129 answers on the span of two weeks. The goal of this second survey was to understand who is OpenRefine audience and what are they relationship with the official community tools (mailing list and Github issue trackers.)]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following the <a href="http://googlerefine.blogspot.ca/2012/10/google-refine-usage-survey-results.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2012 survey</a> which gather 99 answers, I wanted to have a fresh picture on who are OpenRefine users. The 2014 survey received 129 answers on the span of two weeks. The goal of this second survey was to understand who is OpenRefine audience and what are they relationship with the official community tools (mailing list and Github issue trackers.) </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-you-identify-with">Community you identify with<a class="hash-link" href="#community-you-identify-with" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>One of four OpenRefine user identified himself as librarians making this group the the largest of OpenRefine user base. The Researcher and Open Data enthusiasts represent the two second largest group, each representing over 15% of the userbase. Finally Data journalist and Semantic web each represent around 10%.</p><p>We cannot compare directly those results with those from 2012 because in 2012 survey users were able to select multiple answer. However we can notice that in 2012 librarians were not identified as a individual group and are now the largest one. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/1.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/1.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-often-do-you-use-refine">How often do you use Refine<a class="hash-link" href="#how-often-do-you-use-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Taking a slight higher picture the split a 41% using it weekly, a 30% monthly and a 29% less than monthly. Usage frequency remains globally the same between 2012 and 2014.</p><p><strong>2014 Results</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/21.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/21.png" class="inset"></a><p><strong>2012 Results</strong></p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-ay80Gmy0uxI/UH_AaxYo6hI/AAAAAAAABxg/BBAk5L6STro/s1600/03.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-ay80Gmy0uxI/UH_AaxYo6hI/AAAAAAAABxg/BBAk5L6STro/s1600/03.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine">For how long have you been using OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#for-how-long-have-you-been-using-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The split of users remains constant between 2012 and 2014 with </p><ul><li>a third of them using Refine for over two years, </li><li>a third between one and two years and </li><li>a third using OpenRefine for less than one year.</li></ul><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/22.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/22.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="skills">Skills<a class="hash-link" href="#skills" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Both in 2012 and 2014 we asked respondents to rate their skills from one to five. One being a novice in Refine and five being a master. When comparing the result we can see a sharp increase in 2014 of the percentage of user with a skills self evaluated at 3. They represent today 43% of OpenRefine user base. It is interesting that the number of user rating their skills 5 (6 users) and 4  (28 in 2012 and 24 in 2014) remained the same over time. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/3.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/3.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="skills-vs-time">Skills vs time<a class="hash-link" href="#skills-vs-time" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>At a high level, the more experienced user are the higher they will rate their skill.
It takes between 6 months for user to take advantages of OpenRefine. This is only after this time period that user move their skills from a 2/5 to a 3/5. After two years of usage no user rate his skills 1/5.</p><p>On this other side, it take time to master OpenRefine as the proportion of user rating their skills 4 or 6 really increase after two years of usage with still over 50% rating their level between 2 and 3.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/4.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/4.png" class="inset"></a><p>2012 picture is a bit harder to read with because the rating 3/5 is not as prominent as in 2014. However we can see the same trend with the increase of skilled user over time. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/4-2012.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/4-2012.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="skills-vs-frequency">Skills vs frequency<a class="hash-link" href="#skills-vs-frequency" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Very briefly, the more often people use it the better their skills are. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/5.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/5.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="frequency-vs-time">Frequency vs time<a class="hash-link" href="#frequency-vs-time" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>User over two years of experience tends to use it more often but there is no correlation between how long the user has been using OpenRefine and the frequency of usage. As we have seen previously, about 47% of them use it weekly, a third monthly and between 20% and a third less than monthly. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/6.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/6.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="seeking-support">Seeking support<a class="hash-link" href="#seeking-support" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="general-overview">General overview<a class="hash-link" href="#general-overview" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>By order of importance when people need support </p><ul><li>they first learned how to use OpenRefine by themself (91%) using online tutorial or by exploring the interface. </li><li>54% reach to online community (but not the OpenRefine mailing list)</li><li>34% asked someone they know</li><li>Only 19% use the mailing list </li><li>and 7% have attended a formal training. </li></ul><p>It could be interesting to know who are those other online community that provider support for 54% of OpenRefine users.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/71.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/71.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="usage-of-the-mailing-list">Usage of the mailing list<a class="hash-link" href="#usage-of-the-mailing-list" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>We can notice that only 19% of the user are reaching out through the mailing list which is supposed to be main media of communication for the community. When we drill down on who is using the mailing list we realized that this is mainly user with over a year of experience that are using this media. The graphic below show the percentage of user using the mailing list broke down by how long they have been using OpenRefine. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/72.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/72.png" class="inset"></a><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reporting-bugs-and-requesting-new-features">Reporting bugs and requesting new features<a class="hash-link" href="#reporting-bugs-and-requesting-new-features" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Because results are similar for the bug reporting and new feature request, the following analysis will be focus only on the bug reporting answers.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="overview">Overview<a class="hash-link" href="#overview" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Close to 63% of the user are happy with OpenRefine and have nothing to report. However 11% of them want to report something but don't know how. Two hypotheses can be explore:</p><ul><li>Github is too complex for some user to report issue</li><li>The project is missing links and instruction to report issue and request new feature. </li></ul><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/81.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/81.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="breakdown-per-experience-with-refine">Breakdown per experience with Refine<a class="hash-link" href="#breakdown-per-experience-with-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The following graphic shows that only user with over one year experiences with OpenRefine have reported bug or request new feature. Surprisingly over 60% of the user don't know to report something have been using Refine for over a year.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/82.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/82.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="breakdown-per-skills">Breakdown per skills<a class="hash-link" href="#breakdown-per-skills" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>The following graphic shows that the ability to report is not linked with the skills level since user with a skill level of 4 doesn't know how to report. It is interesting that nearly all user self evaluated at 5 did report bug or request feature. </p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/83.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/83.png" class="inset"></a><p>Even user with experience using Refine have difficulties to report bug and request new features. Better guidance is needed and this can be done by either improving</p><ul><li>OpenRefine interface with direct link to Github issue list</li><li>OpenRefine wiki or website with a page describing the process.</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="perception-of-refine">Perception of Refine:<a class="hash-link" href="#perception-of-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-did-you-choose-openrefine">Why did you choose OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#why-did-you-choose-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Both in 2012 and 2014 OpenRefine is chosen for its easy and powerful interface to clean large dataset offering reconciliation option. The fact the project is free and open source is also important for a number of user.</p><p><strong>2012</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/why2012.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/why2012.png" class="inset"></a><p><strong>2014</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/why2014.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/why2014.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="alternative-tools">Alternative tools<a class="hash-link" href="#alternative-tools" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>As in 2012 the tools OpenRefine is benchmarked against split into programming / scripting languages (python, R, MySQL) and spreadsheet based interface like Excel or LibreOffice. </p><p><strong>2012</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/tools2012.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/tools2012.png" class="inset"></a><p><strong>2014</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/tools2014.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="/images/2014survey/tools2014.png" class="inset"></a><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="word-used-to-describe-openrefine">Word used to describe OpenRefine<a class="hash-link" href="#word-used-to-describe-openrefine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>OpenRefine is describe as a data cleaning tool.</p><p><strong>2012</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/describe2012.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/describe2012.png" class="inset"></a><p><strong>2014</strong></p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/describe2014.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/2014survey/describe2014.png" class="inset"></a>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Governance Model for OpenRefine]]></title>
        <id>/2014/04/27/a_governance_model_for_OpenRefine</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2014/04/27/a_governance_model_for_OpenRefine"/>
        <updated>2014-04-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[From its inception until October 2012 Refine development was driven mainly by corporations. Metaweb and Google have committed resources to support and grow Refine for more than two years until Google Refine 2.5 release. With the end of Google support 18 months ago, OpenRefine is working as an indepedant community, relying only on volunteer to maintain the code and support user and contributors.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From its inception until October 2012 Refine development was driven mainly by corporations. Metaweb and Google have committed resources to support and grow Refine for more than two years until Google Refine 2.5 release. With the end of Google support 18 months ago, OpenRefine is working as an indepedant community, relying only on volunteer to maintain the code and support user and contributors.  </p><p>In Fall 2012, I wrote an article on the history of OpenRefine and the need to build a framework for the community. At this time the discussion was focused more on the technical aspect to structure the community (ie <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/openrefine/hiH0KDaTGWY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">moving the code base and documentation to Github</a>) and less on defining a way to work together. </p><p>Today, I feel that we are missing a piece to make this community work. A reference document that will guide our decision and provide visibility for existing and new user on how this community work. Having a governance document will help us to:</p><ul><li>defined responsability within the community,</li><li>have a way to work together and build consensus,</li><li>provide visibility for new user joining the project.  </li></ul><p>I drafted an <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/blob/master/governance.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">governance document on the openrefine.github.com project</a>. The document is not available through the main website. </p><p>I've build the first section based on  the <a href="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/meritocraticGovernanceModel" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">"Meritocratic Governance Model"</a> by University of Oxford and the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1mn3dY6zNyKBU3P_TWoR-RdYpScJDbsXU2TRhwpSAha8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OWIN Project Governance model</a>. Moreover the section regarding <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/blob/master/governance.md#consensus-building" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Consensus building</a> remained to be defined by the community. <strong>You comments and pull request are welcomed (and needed)</strong>. </p><p>Once the governance model defined I wish to see new committers joining the project to help:</p><ul><li>Releasing the final 2.6 version (we are in beta since October 2013)</li><li>Clear the pull request queue (10 pull request are currently pending)</li><li>Help develop the road map for the version 3.0</li></ul><p>[Martin Magdinier]<!-- -->(<a href="http://www.twitter.com/Martin" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">http://www.twitter.com/Martin</a> Magdinier)</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using OpenRefine: a manual]]></title>
        <id>/2013/11/05/using_openrefine</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2013/11/05/using_openrefine"/>
        <updated>2013-11-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[“How do I get started?” is the question we received most]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“How do I get started?”</em> is the question we received most
during our hands-on workshops on data&nbsp;cleaning and enhancing.
OpenRefine is a&nbsp;very powerful tool in the hands of a&nbsp;skilled user,
but how do you become one?
There is a&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wiki</a>,
several <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/Screencasts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">screencasts</a>,
and a&nbsp;list of helpful <a href="https://github.com/OpenRefine/OpenRefine/wiki/External-Resources" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">resources</a>.
However, until recently, no complete OpenRefine manual existed,
so you had to collect documentation from different sources
if you wanted to master OpenRefine.</p><a href="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/using-openrefine.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img loading="lazy" src="https://raw.github.com/OpenRefine/openrefine.github.com/master/images/using-openrefine.jpg" class="inset"></a>This is why we've written an OpenRefine manual called [_Using OpenRefine_](http://www.packtpub.com/openrefine-guide-for-data-analysis-and-linking-dataset-to-the-web/book) that leads you from your first steps to all advanced OpenRefine topics. Using the&nbsp;[entire dataset of the Powerhouse Museum](http://www.powerhousemuseum.com/collection/database/download.php), it lets you experience OpenRefine techniques in a&nbsp;hands-on way, starting from creating a&nbsp;project and inspecting data and gradually evolving towards complex operations. Rather than being a&nbsp;one-directional text, this book offers detailed recipes you can pick whenever you need them.<p><strong>In particular, you'll learn about these topics in <em>Using OpenRefine</em>:</strong></p><ul><li>importing data in various formats</li><li>exploring datasets in a matter of seconds</li><li>applying basic and advanced cell transformations</li><li>dealing with cells that contain multiple values</li><li>creating instantaneous links between datasets</li><li>filtering and partition your data easily with regular expressions</li><li>using named-entity extraction on full-text fields to automatically identify topics</li><li>performing advanced data operations with the General Refine Expression Language</li></ul><p><strong>Get started with OpenRefine right way—for free</strong></p><p>Download the entire <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/9781783289080_Chapter_02.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Chapter 2 of Using OpenRefine">second chapter of the book</a> for free,
so you can already learn about <em>sorting</em>, <em>facets</em>, <em>filters</em>, <em>duplicates</em>, and more.
It's the fastest way to get you up to speed with OpenRefine.
If&nbsp;you also want to learn about advanced transformation
and about connecting your data to the Linked Data cloud,
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Using-OpenRefine/dp/1783289082/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">buy the paperback or e-book</a> today!</p><p>—Ruben and Max<br>authors of <em>Using OpenRefine</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ruben Verborgh</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenRefine History]]></title>
        <id>/2013/10/12/openrefine-history</id>
        <link href="https://wetneb.github.io/new-openrefine-website/blog/2013/10/12/openrefine-history"/>
        <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yesterday David Huynh announced that Google will soon stop its active support of Google Refine and count of community to get more involved to growth Refine.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/openrefine/a3R6afKb4-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">David Huynh announced</a> that Google will soon stop its active support of Google Refine and count of community to get more involved to growth Refine.</p><p>Refine is already a mature data cleaning tool, this change in leadership will be a major challenge for the tool continuity. But first I'd like to clarify what I have read on twitter yesterday night. Google Refine has always been an open source tool and anyone can commit changes, develop an extension or update the wiki. </p><p>Through this post I'd like to give my insight on the reason of this decision and what will be the short terms consequences of it. </p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="google-refine-background">Google Refine Background<a class="hash-link" href="#google-refine-background" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>First let's do a brief history of Google Refine. Google Refine finds its root in the Freebase Gridworks solution developed by Metaweb Technologies, Inc. in May 2010. From its first version, Freebase Gridworks <!-- -->&nbsp;<!-- -->was an open source project. Initially it was a tool designed to support the <a href="http://www.freebase.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Freebase</a> database and community for data cleaning, reconciliation and upload. This historical link with Freebase is still present in Google Refine, as the solution supports reconciliation against Freebase database.</p><p>In July 2010 Google <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.ca/2010/07/deeper-understanding-with-metaweb.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">acquired Metaweb</a> and by extension, Freebase and Gridworks. Freebase Gridworks has been renamed Google Refine and the code and documentation moved to a <a href="http://code.google.com/p/google-refine/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">code.google.com</a> instance. The freshly renamed Google Refine continued to be an open source project for data cleaning. During the 2010 - 2012 period, with the support of Google engineers and the community three upgrade of Google Refine have been made (2.0 ; 2.1 and 2.5). The 2.6 version being on its way (see <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!searchin/google-refine/2.6/google-refine/Bu_3OOtt_mU/oY9jfM8K_VAJ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this discussion for more details</a>).</p><p>Over the last 16 months editing <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.ca" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this blog</a>, I've seen the tremendous interest for Google Refine from various communities. Librarians, journalists, data analysts have been using Google Refine to clean and reconcile their data. <a href="http://code.google.com/p/google-refine/wiki/ReconcilableDataSources" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reconciliation services</a> with more databases have been built, <!-- -->&nbsp;<!-- -->an extension to support <a href="http://refine.deri.ie/docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RDF extension</a> has been written. A vivid community has emerged opening new horizons to Refine capability.</p><p>The user friendly interface helped thousands of non technical users to take control of their data. We are just at the door step of the big data world and Google Refine by lowering the technical barrier to jump in and empower more people for data analysis and processing. As Tom Hirst published today, <a href="http://blog.ouseful.info/2012/10/03/appropriating-it-glue-steps/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Refine is a great entry level Glue Logic tool </a>to create bridges between various application or system.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-google-stop-supporting-google-refine">Why Google stop supporting Google Refine?<a class="hash-link" href="#why-google-stop-supporting-google-refine" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Google Refine is a desktop based application that can work both offline and online (for reconciliation and web scraping). During the two years Refine was with Google, I didn't witness any specific integration with other Google services (like doc, drive or fusion table). Google didn't develop Refine as a cloud based solution, to take advantage of its computing capability. I guess that the current desktop architecture of Google Refine prevents such a migration. My bet is that Google bought Metaweb Technologies for Freebase data and not for Gridworks / Refine functionality and today they don't see the business case to continue to support Refine.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="so-now-what">So, now what?<a class="hash-link" href="#so-now-what" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In the short term, nothing. Google Refine is a stand alone / desktop application, so like most stand alone software, as long as it is installed on your machine, it will run. In a second phase I see two main impacts regarding the end of Google branding and the development of a community supported tool.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-end-of-google-branding">The End of Google Branding<a class="hash-link" href="#the-end-of-google-branding" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Thanks to Google support, Refine is now one of the most mature data cleaning / wrangling tool available. Google branding also help a lot Google Refine marketing and community building. <!-- -->&nbsp;<!-- -->I suppose that Google name was kind of a guarantee on the product capability and maturity for some users and this naming helped to democratize the tool.</p><p>However, I think that losing Google<!-- -->’<!-- -->s name will help Refine in two ways:</p><ol><li><p>Google branding made many new Refine users think that Refine was a cloud application and that data was uploaded on Google servers. That have never been the case, Refine is a local application. However, some users might have been reticent to use Refine for this reason. Maybe a different branding will make them more confident about their data privacy.</p></li><li><p>Reading last nights twitter feed, I realized that most of the people didn't know that Google Refine IS already an open tool. I reckon that the Google branding might have confused most of us, myself included (I created this blog because I didn't know how to edit the wiki). By naming it OpenRefine (or something else), let's hope that more people will engage the community and help with improving it.</p></li></ol><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="openrefine---a-community-support-application">OpenRefine - a Community Support Application<a class="hash-link" href="#openrefine---a-community-support-application" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Please note that OpenRefine branding is not definitive and <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/google-refine/uDUybfL-7Tc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open to discussion</a> on the current mailing list. </p><p>This new step for Google Refine is also a test on how strong its community is. Will there be enough forces to support, maintain and grow the product from a code, documentation and strategy definition perspective? Organizing the current community and welcoming new users and contributors will be the first challenge of OpenRefine.</p><p>We are right now facing a large sheet of white paper, and many things need to be defined from a community management and organization perspective. As the code will be released on Github, little has been defined yet to support the community and articulate the current ecosystem around Google Refine.</p><p>I will be part of this adventure. If you are interested to jump in, this is the right time.
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/google-refine/a3R6afKb4-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Join the conversation</a> on the mailing list and share your thoughts!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Martin Magdinier</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>